<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <link href="http://arxiv.org/api/query?search_query%3Dall%3Aborehole%26id_list%3D%26start%3D0%26max_results%3D2000" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <title type="html">ArXiv Query: search_query=all:borehole&amp;id_list=&amp;start=0&amp;max_results=2000</title>
  <id>http://arxiv.org/api/pohc/MS1ven/nIm1vqUneY1u9+U</id>
  <updated>2018-03-02T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
  <opensearch:totalResults xmlns:opensearch="http://a9.com/-/spec/opensearch/1.1/">53</opensearch:totalResults>
  <opensearch:startIndex xmlns:opensearch="http://a9.com/-/spec/opensearch/1.1/">0</opensearch:startIndex>
  <opensearch:itemsPerPage xmlns:opensearch="http://a9.com/-/spec/opensearch/1.1/">2000</opensearch:itemsPerPage>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1707.05736v1</id>
    <updated>2017-07-18T16:45:09Z</updated>
    <published>2017-07-18T16:45:09Z</published>
    <title>Deep borehole disposal of nuclear waste: US perspective</title>
    <summary>  Radioactive waste disposal in deep boreholes may be more "ready" than
disposal in mined geologic repositories since mankind has greater experience
operating small deep holes - boreholes, than big shallow holes - mines. There
are several thousand precedents for constructing &gt;2 km deep boreholes and
several hundred precedents for disposing long-lived wastes in boreholes.
Borehole disposal is likely to be faster, cheaper, and more flexible than mined
disposal, while also offering greater long-term isolation. Isolation would rely
on the great depth, water density gradients, and reducing conditions to prevent
vertical movement of waste up the borehole.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Patrick V. Brady</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Geoffrey A. Freeze</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Kristopher L. Kuhlman</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Ernest L. Hardin</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>David C. Sassani</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Robert J. MacKinnon</name>
    </author>
    <arxiv:doi xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">10.1016/B978-0-08-100642-9.00004-9</arxiv:doi>
    <link title="doi" href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/B978-0-08-100642-9.00004-9" rel="related"/>
    <arxiv:comment xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">24 pages, 8 figures</arxiv:comment>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1707.05736v1" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1707.05736v1" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1707.01299v1</id>
    <updated>2017-07-05T10:27:47Z</updated>
    <published>2017-07-05T10:27:47Z</published>
    <title>HTEM data improve 3D modelling of aquifers in Paris Basin, France</title>
    <summary>  In Paris Basin, we evaluate how HTEM data complement the usual borehole,
geological and deep seismic data used for modelling aquifer geometries. With
these traditional data, depths between ca. 50 to 300m are often relatively
ill-constrained, as most boreholes lie within the first tens of meters of the
underground and petroleum seismic is blind shallower than ca. 300m. We have
fully reprocessed and re-inverted 540km of flight lines of a SkyTEM survey of
2009, acquired on a 40x12km zone with 400m line spacing. The resistivity model
is first "calibrated" with respect to ca. 50 boreholes available on the study
area. Overall, the correlation between EM resistivity models and the
hydrogeological horizons clearly shows that the geological units in which the
aquifers are developed almost systematically correspond to relative increase of
resistivity, whatever the "background" resistivity environment and the
lithology of the aquifer. In 3D Geomodeller software, this allows interpreting
11 aquifer/aquitar layers along the flight lines and then jointly interpolating
them in 3D along with the borehole data. The resulting model displays 3D
aquifer geometries consistent with the SIGES "reference" regional
hydrogeological model and improves it in between the boreholes and on the
50-300m depth range.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Guillaume Martelet</name>
      <arxiv:affiliation xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">BRGM</arxiv:affiliation>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Pierre-Alexandre Reninger</name>
      <arxiv:affiliation xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">BRGM</arxiv:affiliation>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>José Perrin</name>
      <arxiv:affiliation xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">BRGM</arxiv:affiliation>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Bruno Tourlière</name>
      <arxiv:affiliation xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">BRGM</arxiv:affiliation>
    </author>
    <arxiv:comment xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">Second European Airborne Electromagnetics Conference, Sep 2017,
  Malm\"o, Sweden</arxiv:comment>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1707.01299v1" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1707.01299v1" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/physics/0507025v1</id>
    <updated>2005-07-05T07:08:47Z</updated>
    <published>2005-07-05T07:08:47Z</published>
    <title>Comparative study of P and S wave amplitudes of acoustic logging through
  solid formations : contribution to the knowledge of in situ stresses and
  fractures</title>
    <summary>  In order to compare the ratios between the amplitudes of P and S acoustic
waves drawn from various boreholes, we have defined a specific wave parameter
called magnitude : for each shot, we have added the maximum positive amplitude
values and the absolute values of the minimum negative amplitudes of a given
wave recorded at different depths. In compact formations, the difference
between the logarithms of the magnitudes of S and P waves provides a value that
appears to be characteristic of the state of stress of the domain where a
borehole is drilled. Accidents between those formations, such as fractures or
sedimentary joints can be determined, and breakouts well distinguished.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>André Rousseau</name>
      <arxiv:affiliation xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">OASU</arxiv:affiliation>
    </author>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/physics/0507025v1" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/physics/0507025v1" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1701.00704v1</id>
    <updated>2017-01-03T14:44:49Z</updated>
    <published>2017-01-03T14:44:49Z</published>
    <title>Fracture imaging within a granitic rock aquifer using multiple-offset
  single-hole and cross-hole GPR reflection data</title>
    <summary>  The sparsely spaced highly permeable fractures of the granitic rock aquifer
at Stang-er-Brune (Brittany, France) form a well-connected fracture network of
high permeability but unknown geometry. Previous work based on optical and
acoustic logging together with single-hole and cross-hole flowmeter data
acquired in 3 neighboring boreholes (70-100 m deep) have identified the most
important permeable fractures crossing the boreholes and their hydraulic
connections. To constrain possible flow paths by estimating the geometries of
known and previously unknown fractures, we have acquired, processed and
interpreted multifold, single- and cross-hole GPR data using 100 and 250 MHz
antennas. The GPR data processing scheme consisting of time-zero corrections,
scaling, bandpass filtering and F-X deconvolution, eigenvector filtering,
muting, pre-stack Kirchhoff depth migration and stacking was used to
differentiate fluid-filled fracture reflections from source-generated noise.
The final stacked and pre-stack depth-migrated GPR sections provide
high-resolution images of individual fractures (dipping 30-90{\deg}) in the
surroundings (2-20 m for the 100 MHz antennas; 2-12 m for the 250 MHz antennas)
of each borehole in a 2D plane projection that are of superior quality to those
obtained from single-offset sections. Most fractures previously identified from
hydraulic testing can be correlated to reflections in the single-hole data.
Several previously unknown major near vertical fractures have also been
identified away from the boreholes.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>C. Dorn</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>N. Linde</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>J. Doetsch</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>T. Le Borgne</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>O. Bour</name>
    </author>
    <arxiv:doi xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">10.1016/j.jappgeo.2011.01.010</arxiv:doi>
    <link title="doi" href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jappgeo.2011.01.010" rel="related"/>
    <arxiv:journal_ref xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">Journal of Applied Geophysics, 78, 123-132 (2012)</arxiv:journal_ref>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1701.00704v1" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1701.00704v1" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1702.02633v2</id>
    <updated>2017-09-03T14:47:35Z</updated>
    <published>2017-02-08T22:04:28Z</published>
    <title>Pseudo-Outcrop Visualization of Borehole Images and Core Scans</title>
    <summary>  A pseudo-outcrop visualization is demonstrated for borehole and full-diameter
rock core images to augment the ubiquitous unwrapped cylinder view and thereby
to assist non-specialist interpreters. The pseudo-outcrop visualization is
equivalent to a nonlinear projection of the image from borehole to earth frame
of reference that creates a solid volume sliced longitudinally to reveal two or
more faces in which the orientations of geological features indicate what is
observed in the subsurface. A proxy for grain size is used to modulate the
external dimensions of the plot to mimic profiles seen in real outcrops. The
volume is created from a mixture of geological boundary elements and texture,
the latter being the residue after the sum of boundary elements is subtracted
from the original data. In the case of measurements from wireline
microresistivity tools, whose circumferential coverage is substantially less
than 100%, the missing circumferential data is first inpainted using multiscale
directional transforms, which decompose the image into its elemental building
structures, before reconstructing the full image. The pseudo-outcrop view
enables direct observation of the angular relationships between features and
aids visual comparison between borehole and core images, especially for the
interested non-specialist.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Evgeny M. Mirkes</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Alexander N. Gorban</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Jeremy Levesley</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Peter A. S. Elkington</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>James A. Whetton</name>
    </author>
    <arxiv:doi xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">10.1007/s11004-017-9701-2</arxiv:doi>
    <link title="doi" href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s11004-017-9701-2" rel="related"/>
    <arxiv:comment xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">Updated and corrected version with extended set of figures</arxiv:comment>
    <arxiv:journal_ref xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">Mathematical Geosciences, 2017</arxiv:journal_ref>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1702.02633v2" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1702.02633v2" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/physics/0312069v2</id>
    <updated>2006-04-21T08:05:57Z</updated>
    <published>2003-12-11T13:04:37Z</published>
    <title>Influence of squirt flow on fundamental guided waves propagation in
  borehole embedded in saturated porous media</title>
    <summary>  In this paper, the reservoir is modeled by homogeneous two-phase media based
on BISQ model. We focus on the effects of the squirt flow on the fundamental
guided waves propagation in borehole embedded in saturated porous media excited
by monopole, dipole and quadrupole point sources. The full waveforms acoustic
logging in a fluid-filled borehole are simulated. The curves of velocity
dispersion, attenuation coefficients and excitation of the fundamental guided
waves have shown that velocity dispersions are almost independent of the
characteristic squirt flow length, attenuations of guided waves are enhanced
due to the squirt flow, and excitations of guided waves are decreased due to
the squirt flow. It is possible to estimate the characteristic squirt flow
length by attenuation coefficients of the guided waves from acoustical logging
data.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Zhi-Wen. Cui</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Jin-Xia. Liu</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Ke-Xie. Wang</name>
    </author>
    <arxiv:comment xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">all 18 pages 6 figures</arxiv:comment>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/physics/0312069v2" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/physics/0312069v2" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/physics/0503153v1</id>
    <updated>2005-03-17T18:56:02Z</updated>
    <published>2005-03-17T18:56:02Z</published>
    <title>Relationship between acoustic body waves and in situ stresses around a
  borehole</title>
    <summary>  This paper shows that there are three types of shape of acoustic body waves
propagating inside competent and homogeneous formations penetrated by a
borehole : simple, double, and resonant. This fact is connected to the
modifications undergone by the area located around a well after drilling in
relation to in situ state of stress. There are overstressed and understressed
vertical cylindrical zones with "bubble-shaped" cross-sections, in which
acoustic body waves are supposed to reflect. The horizontal size and the shape
of the stress modified areas depend on the values of (K1+K2)/2 - with K1=SH/Sv
(the overburden pressure) and K2=Sh/Sv -, that is to say on the in situ
horizontal stress and the anisotropy of this stress. The calculation of the
velocities of the P and S double waves allows us to evaluate the radial
thicknesses of these stress modified areas. As their values are different
according to whether they result from P or S waves, we propose an explanation
based on their wavelengths. The comparisons with other works on the in situ
stress of the studied boreholes allow us to propose a method for evaluating the
horizontal stress and its anisotropy, thanks to the estimation of the value
(K1+K2)/2.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>André Rousseau</name>
      <arxiv:affiliation xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">OASU</arxiv:affiliation>
    </author>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/physics/0503153v1" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/physics/0503153v1" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1107.4905v1</id>
    <updated>2011-07-25T11:42:58Z</updated>
    <published>2011-07-25T11:42:58Z</published>
    <title>Bayesian hierarchical modeling for temperature reconstruction from
  geothermal data</title>
    <summary>  We present a Bayesian hierarchical modeling approach to paleoclimate
reconstruction using borehole temperature profiles. The approach relies on
modeling heat conduction in solids via the heat equation with step function,
surface boundary conditions. Our analysis includes model error and assumes that
the boundary conditions are random processes. The formulation also enables
separation of measurement error and model error. We apply the analysis to data
from nine borehole temperature records from the San Rafael region in Utah. We
produce ground surface temperature histories with uncertainty estimates for the
past 400 years. We pay special attention to use of prior parameter models that
illustrate borrowing strength in a combined analysis for all nine boreholes. In
addition, we review selected sensitivity analyses.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Jenný Brynjarsdóttir</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>L. Mark Berliner</name>
    </author>
    <arxiv:doi xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">10.1214/10-AOAS452</arxiv:doi>
    <link title="doi" href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1214/10-AOAS452" rel="related"/>
    <arxiv:comment xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">Published in at http://dx.doi.org/10.1214/10-AOAS452 the Annals of
  Applied Statistics (http://www.imstat.org/aoas/) by the Institute of
  Mathematical Statistics (http://www.imstat.org)</arxiv:comment>
    <arxiv:journal_ref xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">Annals of Applied Statistics 2011, Vol. 5, No. 2B, 1328-1359</arxiv:journal_ref>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1107.4905v1" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1107.4905v1" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="stat.AP" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="stat.AP" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/physics/0511242v1</id>
    <updated>2005-11-29T10:23:33Z</updated>
    <published>2005-11-29T10:23:33Z</published>
    <title>Acoustic identification of a poroelastic cylinder</title>
    <summary>  We show how to cope with the acoustic identification of poroelastic materials
when the specimen is in the form of a cylinder. We apply our formulation, based
on the Biot model, approximated by the equivalent elastic solid model, to a
long bone-like or borehole sample specimen probed by low frequency sound.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Zine Fellah</name>
      <arxiv:affiliation xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">LMA</arxiv:affiliation>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Jean-Philippe Groby</name>
      <arxiv:affiliation xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">LMA, LATF</arxiv:affiliation>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Erick Ogam</name>
      <arxiv:affiliation xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">LMA</arxiv:affiliation>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Thierry Scotti</name>
      <arxiv:affiliation xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">LMA</arxiv:affiliation>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Armand Wirgin</name>
      <arxiv:affiliation xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">LMA</arxiv:affiliation>
    </author>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/physics/0511242v1" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/physics/0511242v1" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="physics.class-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.class-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/physics/0401047v5</id>
    <updated>2005-04-07T01:57:29Z</updated>
    <published>2004-01-11T02:49:31Z</published>
    <title>Gravitation, the 'Dark Matter' Effect and the Fine Structure Constant</title>
    <summary>  Gravitational anomalies such as the mine/borehole g anomaly, the
near-flatness of the spiral galaxy rotation-velocity curves, currently
interpreted as a `dark matter' effect, the absence of that effect in ordinary
elliptical galaxies, and the ongoing problems in accurately determining
Newton's gravitational constant G_N are explained by a generalisation of the
Newtonian theory of gravity to a fluid-flow formalism with one new
dimensionless constant. By analysing the borehole data this constant is shown
to be the fine structure constant alpha=1/137. The spiral galaxy `dark matter'
effect and the globular cluster `black hole' masses are then correctly
predicted. This formalism also explains the cause of the long-standing
uncertainties in G_N and leads to the introduction of a fundamental
gravitational constant G not = G_N with value G=(6.6526 +/- 0.013)x 10^-11
m^3s^{-2}kg^{-1}. The occurrence of alpha implies that space has a quantum
structure, and we have the first evidence of quantum gravity effects.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Reginald T. Cahill</name>
      <arxiv:affiliation xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">Flinders University</arxiv:affiliation>
    </author>
    <arxiv:comment xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">21 pages, 4 eps figures. Extended published version</arxiv:comment>
    <arxiv:journal_ref xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">Apeiron 12 (2005) 144-177</arxiv:journal_ref>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/physics/0401047v5" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/physics/0401047v5" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="physics.gen-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.gen-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/physics/0512109v1</id>
    <updated>2005-12-13T05:58:09Z</updated>
    <published>2005-12-13T05:58:09Z</published>
    <title>3-Space In-Flow Theory of Gravity: Boreholes, Blackholes and the Fine
  Structure Constant</title>
    <summary>  A theory of 3-space explains the phenomenon of gravity as arising from the
time-dependence and inhomogeneity of the differential flow of this 3-space. The
emergent theory of gravity has two gravitational constants: G - Newton's
constant, and a dimensionless constant - alpha. Various experiments and
astronomical observations have shown that alpha is the fine structure constant
1/137. Here we analyse the Greenland Ice Shelf and Nevada Test Site borehole g
anomalies, and confirm with increased precision this value of alpha. This and
other successful tests of this theory of gravity, including the supermassive
black holes in globular clusters and galaxies, and the `dark-matter' effect in
spiral galaxies, demonstrates the validity of this theory of gravity. This
success implies that Newtonian gravity was fundamentally flawed from the
beginning.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Reginald T. Cahill</name>
      <arxiv:affiliation xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">Flinders University</arxiv:affiliation>
    </author>
    <arxiv:comment xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">12 pages, 7 figures</arxiv:comment>
    <arxiv:journal_ref xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">Prog.Phys. 2 (2006) 9-16</arxiv:journal_ref>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/physics/0512109v1" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/physics/0512109v1" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="physics.gen-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.gen-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/0806.2399v1</id>
    <updated>2008-06-14T20:12:06Z</updated>
    <published>2008-06-14T20:12:06Z</published>
    <title>Thermal Conductivity from Core and Well log Data</title>
    <summary>  The relationships between thermal conductivity and other petrophysical
properties have been analysed for a borehole drilled in a Tertiary Flysch
sequence. We establish equations that permit us to predict rock thermal
conductivity from logging data. A regression analysis of thermal conductivity,
bulk density, and sonic velocity yields thermal conductivity with an average
accuracy of better than 0.2 W/(m K). As a second step, logging data is used to
compute a lithological depth profile, which in turn is used to calculate a
thermal conductivity profile. From a comparison of the conductivity-depth
profile and the laboratory data it can be concluded that thermal conductivity
can be computed with an accuracy of less than 0.3 W/(m K)from conventional
wireline data. The comparison of two different models shows that this approach
can be practical even if old and incomplete logging data is used. The results
can be used to infer thermal conductivity for boreholes without appropriate
core data that are drilled in a similar geological setting.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Andreas Hartmann</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Volker Rath</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Christoph Clauser</name>
    </author>
    <arxiv:doi xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">10.1016/j.ijrmms.2005.05.015</arxiv:doi>
    <link title="doi" href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ijrmms.2005.05.015" rel="related"/>
    <arxiv:comment xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">18 pages, 9 figure, 3 tables</arxiv:comment>
    <arxiv:journal_ref xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">Int. J. Rock Mech. and Mining Sc., 42(7-8), 1042-1055, 2005</arxiv:journal_ref>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/0806.2399v1" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/0806.2399v1" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1609.09457v2</id>
    <updated>2017-04-28T15:48:50Z</updated>
    <published>2016-09-29T18:35:23Z</published>
    <title>From arteries to boreholes: Steady-state response of a poroelastic
  cylinder to fluid injection</title>
    <summary>  The radially outward flow of fluid into a porous medium occurs in many
practical problems, from transport across vascular walls to the pressurisation
of boreholes. As the driving pressure becomes non-negligible relative to the
stiffness of the solid structure, the poromechanical coupling between the fluid
and the solid has an increasingly strong impact on the flow. For very large
pressures or very soft materials, as is the case for hydraulic fracturing and
arterial flows, this coupling can lead to large deformations and, hence, to
strong deviations from a classical, linear-poroelastic response. Here, we study
this problem by analysing the steady-state response of a poroelastic cylinder
to fluid injection. We consider the qualitative and quantitative impacts of
kinematic and constitutive nonlinearity, highlighting the strong impact of
deformation-dependent permeability. We show that the wall thickness (thick vs.
thin) and the outer boundary condition (free vs. constrained) play a central
role in controlling the mechanics.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Lucy C. Auton</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Christopher W. MacMinn</name>
    </author>
    <arxiv:doi xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">10.1098/rspa.2016.0753</arxiv:doi>
    <link title="doi" href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1098/rspa.2016.0753" rel="related"/>
    <arxiv:journal_ref xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">Proceedings of the Royal Society A 473, 20160753 (2017)</arxiv:journal_ref>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1609.09457v2" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1609.09457v2" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="physics.flu-dyn" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.flu-dyn" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="cond-mat.soft" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1712.08261v1</id>
    <updated>2017-12-22T00:36:19Z</updated>
    <published>2017-12-22T00:36:19Z</published>
    <title>From arteries to boreholes: Transient response of a poroelastic cylinder
  to fluid injection</title>
    <summary>  The radially outward flow of fluid through a porous medium occurs in many
practical problems, from transport across vascular walls to the pressurisation
of boreholes in the subsurface. When the driving pressure is non-negligible
relative to the stiffness of the solid structure, the poromechanical coupling
between the fluid and the solid can control both the steady-state and the
transient mechanics of the system. Very large pressures or very soft materials
lead to large deformations of the solid skeleton, which introduce kinematic and
constitutive nonlinearity that can have a nontrivial impact on these mechanics.
Here, we study the transient response of a poroelastic cylinder to sudden fluid
injection. We consider the impacts of kinematic and constitutive nonlinearity,
both separately and in combination, and we highlight the central role of
driving method in the evolution of the response. We show that the various
facets of nonlinearity may either accelerate or decelerate the transient
response relative to linear poroelasticity, depending on the boundary
conditions and the initial geometry, and that an imposed fluid pressure leads
to a much faster response than an imposed fluid flux.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Lucy C. Auton</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Christopher W. MacMinn</name>
    </author>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1712.08261v1" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1712.08261v1" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="physics.flu-dyn" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.flu-dyn" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="cond-mat.soft" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/0806.2042v1</id>
    <updated>2008-06-12T10:54:26Z</updated>
    <published>2008-06-12T10:54:26Z</published>
    <title>Measurements of radio propagation in rock salt for the detection of
  high-energy neutrinos</title>
    <summary>  We present measurements of the transmission of radio/microwave pulses through
salt in the Cote Blanche salt mine operated by the North American Salt Company
in St. Mary Parish, Louisiana. These results are from data taken in the
southwestern region of the 1500 ft. (457 m) deep level of the mine on our third
and most recent visit to the mine. We transmitted and received a fast,
high-power, broadband pulse from within three vertical boreholes that were
drilled to depths of 100 ft. (30 m) and 200 ft. below the 1500 ft. level using
three different pairs of dipole antennas whose bandwidths span 125 to 900 MHz.
By measuring the relative strength of the received pulses between boreholes
with separations of 50 m and 169 m, we deduce the attenuation of the signal
attributed to the salt medium. We fit the frequency dependence of the
attenuation to a power law and find the best fit field attenuation lengths to
be 93 \pm 7 m at 150 MHz, 63 \pm 3 m at 300 MHz, and 36 \pm 2 m at 800 MHz.
This is the most precise measurement of radio attenuation in a natural salt
formation to date. We assess the implications of this measurement for a future
neutrino detector in salt.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Amy Connolly</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Abigail Goodhue</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Christian Miki</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Ryan Nichol</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>David Saltzberg</name>
    </author>
    <arxiv:doi xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">10.1016/j.nima.2008.11.008</arxiv:doi>
    <link title="doi" href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.nima.2008.11.008" rel="related"/>
    <arxiv:comment xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">33 pages, 10 figures. Submitted to Nuclear Inst. and Methods in
  Physics Research, A</arxiv:comment>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/0806.2042v1" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/0806.2042v1" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="astro-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="astro-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/0908.1962v2</id>
    <updated>2009-08-13T20:09:13Z</updated>
    <published>2009-08-13T19:59:40Z</published>
    <title>Numerical Modeling of Complex Porous Media For Borehole Applications</title>
    <summary>  The diffusion/relaxation behavior of polarized spins of pore filling fluid,
as often probed by NMR relaxometry, is widely used to extract information on
the pore-geometry. Such information is further interpreted as an indicator of
the key transport property of the formation in the oil industry. As the
importance of reservoirs with complex pore geometry grows, so does the need for
deeper understanding of how these properties are inter-related. Numerical
modeling of relevant physical processes using a known pore geometry promises to
be an effective tool in such endeavor. Using a suite of numerical techniques
based on random-walk (RW) and Lattice-Boltzmann (LB) algorithms, we compare
sandstone and carbonate pore geometries in their impact on NMR and flow
properties. For NMR relaxometry, both laboratory measurement and simulation
were done on the same source to address some of the long-standing issues in its
borehole applications. Through a series of "numerical experiments" in which the
interfacial relaxation properties of the pore matrix is varied systematically,
we study the effect of a variable surface relaxivity while fully incorporating
the complexity of the pore geometry. From combined RW and LB simulations, we
also obtain diffusion-convection propagator and compare the result with
experimental and network-simulation counterparts.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Seungoh Ryu</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Weishu Zhao</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Gabriela Leu</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Philip M. Singer</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Hyung Joon Cho</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Youngseuk Keehm</name>
    </author>
    <arxiv:comment xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">6 pages, 6 color figures, Workshop GeoX10</arxiv:comment>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/0908.1962v2" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/0908.1962v2" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="cond-mat.soft" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="cond-mat.soft" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1101.1473v1</id>
    <updated>2011-01-07T16:52:43Z</updated>
    <published>2011-01-07T16:52:43Z</published>
    <title>Identification of earthquake precursors in the hydrogeochemical and
  geoacoustic data for the Kamchatka peninsula by flicker-noise spectroscopy</title>
    <summary>  A phenomenological systems approach for identifying potential precursors in
multiple signals of different types for the same local seismically active
region is proposed based on the assumption that a large earthquake may be
preceded by a system reconfiguration (preparation) at different time and space
scales. A nonstationarity factor introduced within the framework of
flicker-noise spectroscopy, a statistical physics approach to the analysis of
time series, is used as the dimensionless criterion for detecting qualitative
(precursory) changes within relatively short time intervals in arbitrary
signals. Nonstationarity factors for chlorine-ion concentration variations in
the underground water of two boreholes on the Kamchatka peninsula and
geacoustic emissions in a deep borehole within the same seismic zone are
studied together in the time frame around a large earthquake on October 8,
2001. It is shown that nonstationarity factor spikes (potential precursors)
take place in the interval from 70 to 50 days before the earthquake for the
hydrogeochemical data and at 29 and 6 days in advance for the geoacoustic data.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>G. V. Ryabinin</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Yu. S. Polyakov</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>V. A. Gavrilov</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>S. F. Timashev</name>
    </author>
    <arxiv:doi xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">10.5194/nhess-11-541-2011</arxiv:doi>
    <link title="doi" href="http://dx.doi.org/10.5194/nhess-11-541-2011" rel="related"/>
    <arxiv:comment xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">8 pages, 4 figures; to be published in Nat. Hazards Earth Syst. Sci</arxiv:comment>
    <arxiv:journal_ref xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">Nat. Haz. Earth Syst. Sci. 11, 541-548 (2011)</arxiv:journal_ref>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1101.1473v1" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1101.1473v1" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="physics.data-an" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.data-an" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1212.2763v1</id>
    <updated>2012-12-12T10:34:18Z</updated>
    <published>2012-12-12T10:34:18Z</published>
    <title>Thermal Fracturing of Geothermal Wells and the Effects of Borehole
  Orientation</title>
    <summary>  An enhanced geothermal system (EGS) expands the potential of geothermal
energy by enabling the exploitation of regions that lack conventional
hydrothermal resources. The EGS subsurface system is created by engineering
enhanced flow paths between injection and production wells. Hydraulic
stimulation of existing fracture networks has been successfully achieved for
unconventional geothermal resources. More recently proposed concepts increase
the use of drilled wellbores in hard rock to connect the injection and
production wells. The present work investigates the long-term thermal effects
of deviated geothermal wellbores and studies how the cooling of the borehole
wall results in thermally induced tensile fractures. The results show that
induced fractures are created by a combination of in situ and thermal stresses,
and that the extent to which thermally induced tensile wall fractures are
created largely depends on how the wellbores are oriented with respect to the
pre-existing stresses of the reservoir. If the system is not optimized with
respect to in situ stresses, the risk of wellbore instability becomes severe
within less than a year of production. In contrast, if the orientation of the
wellbores is optimized, thermally induced instabilities can be completely
excluded as potential risks for the operational lifetime of the system.
Furthermore, our results show that the thermal failure process strongly depends
on the temperature of the injected water but is only weakly affected by the
injection rate.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Kjetil M. D. Hals</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Inga Berre</name>
    </author>
    <arxiv:comment xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">10 pages, 5 figures, submitted to Geothermics</arxiv:comment>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1212.2763v1" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1212.2763v1" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="cond-mat.mtrl-sci" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.flu-dyn" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1312.3981v1</id>
    <updated>2013-12-13T23:11:23Z</updated>
    <published>2013-12-13T23:11:23Z</published>
    <title>Joint multi-mode dispersion extraction in Fourier and space time domains</title>
    <summary>  In this paper we present a novel broadband approach for the extraction of
dispersion curves of multiple time frequency overlapped dispersive modes such
as in borehole acoustic data. The new approach works jointly in the Fourier and
space time domains and, in contrast to existing space time approaches that
mainly work for time frequency separated signals, efficiently handles multiple
signals with significant time frequency overlap. The proposed method begins by
exploiting the slowness (phase and group) and time location estimates based on
frequency-wavenumber (f-k) domain sparsity penalized broadband dispersion
extraction method as presented in \cite{AeronTSP2011}. In this context we first
present a Cramer Rao Bound (CRB) analysis for slowness estimation in the (f-k)
domain and show that for the f-k domain broadband processing, group slowness
estimates have more variance than the phase slowness estimates and time
location estimates. In order to improve the group slowness estimates we exploit
the time compactness property of the modes to effectively represent the data as
a linear superposition of time compact space time propagators parameterized by
the phase and group slowness. A linear least squares estimation algorithm in
the space time domain is then used to obtain improved group slowness estimates.
The performance of the method is demonstrated on real borehole acoustic data
sets.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Sandip Bose</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Shuchin Aeron</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Henri-Pierre Valero</name>
    </author>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1312.3981v1" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1312.3981v1" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="cs.IT" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="math.IT" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1611.08797v1</id>
    <updated>2016-11-27T06:49:33Z</updated>
    <published>2016-11-27T06:49:33Z</published>
    <title>A Novel, Compact Optical Device for Estimating the Methane Emissions in
  Geological Environment</title>
    <summary>  Quantifying spontaneous, fugitive and venting related methane emissions are
often difficult and cumbersome. However, auditing the methane emissions due to
conventional and un-conventional hydrocarbon exploitation techniques are
becoming necessary. Present generation compact chemical sensors are slower,
degrade very fast, and are sensitive broad-spectrum gases. On the other hand,
optical sensors are very fast in detection of gases and more precise and can be
easily employed in various environments like boreholes and soils. In this
study, we report development of an optical sensor that is methane specific,
fast for real time applications and has tremendous application potential in the
exploration of coal bed methane and other hydrocarbon reserves with methane as
a major constituent. The detection process is based on the principle of
spectroscopic absorption of light. The detector, NiSi Schottky diode, was
fabricated and characterized exclusively for the 1.65 um, narrow bandwidth
methane absorption. The probe is of 20 cm length and comprises of a laser
source and the NiSi detector aligned optically. This probe can be employed in
boreholes, mine vents and soil layers for measuring real-time fluxes in methane
concentrations. From the laboratory based experiments it is observed that the
detection limits of the developed device is very low (3% by volume) and the
response time of detection is very rapid (about 2 seconds). Based on the
materials used, fabrication procedures adopted, sensitivity of the device and
its compactness, the developed sensor can be considered as a novel, economic
device for exploration of coal bed methane.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Sandipta Roy</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Ramakrishnan Desikan</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Siddhartha P. Duttagupta</name>
    </author>
    <arxiv:comment xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">14 pages 9 figures</arxiv:comment>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1611.08797v1" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1611.08797v1" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="physics.ins-det" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.ins-det" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1701.01877v1</id>
    <updated>2017-01-07T20:27:39Z</updated>
    <published>2017-01-07T20:27:39Z</published>
    <title>Inferring transport characteristics in a fractured rock aquifer by
  combining single-hole GPR reflection monitoring and tracer test data</title>
    <summary>  Investigations of solute transport in fractured rock aquifers often rely on
tracer test data acquired at a limited number of observation points. Such data
do not, by themselves, allow detailed assessments of the spreading of the
injected tracer plume. To better understand the transport behavior in a
granitic aquifer, we combine tracer test data with single-hole
ground-penetrating radar (GPR) reflection monitoring data. Five successful
tracer tests were performed under various experimental conditions between two
boreholes 6 m apart. For each experiment, saline tracer was injected into a
previously identified packed-off transmissive fracture while repeatedly
acquiring single-hole GPR reflection profiles together with electrical
conductivity logs in the pumping borehole. By analyzing depth-migrated GPR
difference images together with tracer breakthrough curves and associated
simplified flow and transport modeling, we estimate (1) the number, the
connectivity, and the geometry of fractures that contribute to tracer
transport, (2) the velocity and the mass of tracer that was carried along each
flow path, and (3) the effective transport parameters of the identified flow
paths. We find a qualitative agreement when comparing the time evolution of GPR
reflectivity strengths at strategic locations in the formation with those
arising from simulated transport. The discrepancies are on the same order as
those between observed and simulated breakthrough curves at the outflow
locations. The rather subtle and repeatable GPR signals provide useful and
complementary information to tracer test data acquired at the outflow locations
and may help us to characterize transport phenomena in fractured rock aquifers.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>C. Dorn</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>N. Linde</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>T. Le Borgne</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>O. Bour</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>M. Kleptikova</name>
    </author>
    <arxiv:doi xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">10.1029/2011WR011739</arxiv:doi>
    <link title="doi" href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1029/2011WR011739" rel="related"/>
    <arxiv:journal_ref xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">Water Resources Research, 48, W11521 (2012)</arxiv:journal_ref>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1701.01877v1" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1701.01877v1" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1701.01881v1</id>
    <updated>2017-01-07T20:42:52Z</updated>
    <published>2017-01-07T20:42:52Z</published>
    <title>Conditioning of stochastic 3-D fracture networks to hydrological and
  geophysical data</title>
    <summary>  The geometry and connectivity of fractures exert a strong influence on the
flow and transport properties of fracture networks. We present a novel approach
to stochastically generate three-dimensional discrete networks of connected
fractures that are conditioned to hydrological and geophysical data. A
hierarchical rejection sampling algorithm is used to draw realizations from the
posterior probability density function at different conditioning levels. The
method is applied to a well-studied granitic formation using data acquired
within two boreholes located 6 m apart. The prior models include 27 fractures
with their geometry (position and orientation) bounded by information derived
from single-hole ground-penetrating radar (GPR) data acquired during saline
tracer tests and optical televiewer logs. Eleven cross-hole hydraulic
connections between fractures in neighboring boreholes and the order in which
the tracer arrives at different fractures are used for conditioning.
Furthermore, the networks are conditioned to the observed relative hydraulic
importance of the different hydraulic connections by numerically simulating the
flow response. Among the conditioning data considered, constraints on the
relative flow contributions were the most effective in determining the
variability among the network realizations. Nevertheless, we find that the
posterior model space is strongly determined by the imposed prior bounds.
Strong prior bounds were derived from GPR measurements and helped to make the
approach computationally feasible. We analyze a set of 230 posterior
realizations that reproduce all data given their uncertainties assuming the
same uniform transmissivity in all fractures. The posterior models provide
valuable statistics on length scales and density of connected fractures, as
well as their connectivity.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>C. Dorn</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>N. Linde</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>T. Le Borgne</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>O. Bour</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>J. -R. de Dreuzy</name>
    </author>
    <arxiv:doi xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">10.1016/j.advwatres.2013.10.005</arxiv:doi>
    <link title="doi" href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.advwatres.2013.10.005" rel="related"/>
    <arxiv:journal_ref xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">Advances in Water Resources, 62, 79-89 (2013)</arxiv:journal_ref>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1701.01881v1" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1701.01881v1" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1710.00855v1</id>
    <updated>2017-10-02T18:31:14Z</updated>
    <published>2017-10-02T18:31:14Z</published>
    <title>Feasibility of Direct Disposal of Salt Waste from Electochemical
  Processing of Spent Nuclear Fuel</title>
    <summary>  The US Department of Energy decided in 2000 to treat its sodium-bonded spent
nuclear fuel, produced for experiments on breeder reactors, with an
electrochemical process. The metallic waste produced is to be cast into ingots
and the salt waste further processed to form a ceramic waste form for disposal
in a mined repository. However, alternative disposal pathways for metallic and
salt waste streams are being investigated that may reduce the processing
complexity. As summarized here, performance assessments analyzing the direct
disposal the salt waste demonstrate that both mined repositories in salt and
deep boreholes in basement crystalline rock can easily accommodate the salt
waste. Also summarized here is an analysis of the feasibility of transporting
the salt waste in a proposed vessel. The vessel is viable for transport to and
disposal in a generic mined repository in salt or deep borehole but a portion
of the salt waste would need to be diluted for disposal in the Waste Isolation
Pilot Plant. The generally positive results continue to demonstrate the
feasibility of direct disposal of salt waste after electrochemical processing
of spent nuclear fuel.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Rob P Rechard</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Teklu Hadgu</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Yifeng Wang</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Larry C. Sanchez</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Patrick McDaniel</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Corey Skinner</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Nima Fathi</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Steven Frank</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Michael Patterson</name>
    </author>
    <arxiv:comment xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">8 pages, 7 figures, Presented at International High-Level Radioactive
  Waste Management (IHLRWM2017), April 9-13, 2017, Charlotte, NC</arxiv:comment>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1710.00855v1" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1710.00855v1" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="physics.app-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.app-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.ins-det" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1310.4689v1</id>
    <updated>2013-10-17T13:04:26Z</updated>
    <published>2013-10-17T13:04:26Z</published>
    <title>Morphological analysis of stylolites for paleostress estimation in
  limestones surrounding the Andra Underground Research Laboratory site</title>
    <summary>  We develop and test a methodology to infer paleostress from the morphology of
stylolites within borehole cores. This non-destructive method is based on the
analysis of the stylolite trace along the outer cylindrical surface of the
cores. It relies on an automatic digitization of high-resolution photographs
and on the spatial Fourier spectrum analysis of the stylolite traces. We test
and show, on both synthetic and natural examples, that the information from
this outer cylindrical surface is equivalent to the one obtained from the
destructive planar sections traditionally used. The assessment of paleostress
from the stylolite morphology analysis is made using a recent theoretical
model, which links the morphological properties to the physical processes
acting during stylolite evolution. This model shows that two scaling regimes
are to be expected for the stylolite height power spectrum, separated by a
cross-over length that depends on the magnitude of the paleostress during
formation. We develop a non linear fit method to automatically extract the
cross-over lengths from the digitized stylolite profiles. Results on cores from
boreholes drilled in the surroundings of the Andra Underground Research
Laboratory located at Bure, France, show that different groups of sedimentary
stylolites can be distinguished, and correspond to different estimated vertical
paleostress values. For the Oxfordian formation, one group of stylolites
indicate a paleostress of around 10 MPa, while another group yields 15 MPa. For
the Dogger formation, two stylolites indicate a paleostress of around 10 MPa,
while others appear to have stopped growing at paleostresses between 30 and 22
MPa, starting at an erosion phase that initiated in the late Cretaceous and
continues today. This method has a high potential for further applications on
reservoirs or other geological contexts where stylolites are present.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Alexandra Rolland</name>
      <arxiv:affiliation xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">IPGS, ANDRA</arxiv:affiliation>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Renaud Toussaint</name>
      <arxiv:affiliation xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">IPGS</arxiv:affiliation>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Patrick Baud</name>
      <arxiv:affiliation xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">IPGS</arxiv:affiliation>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Nathalie Conil</name>
      <arxiv:affiliation xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">ANDRA</arxiv:affiliation>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Philippe Landrein</name>
      <arxiv:affiliation xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">ANDRA</arxiv:affiliation>
    </author>
    <arxiv:doi xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">10.1016/j.ijrmms.2013.08.021</arxiv:doi>
    <link title="doi" href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ijrmms.2013.08.021" rel="related"/>
    <arxiv:comment xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">International Journal of Rock Mechanics and Mining Sciences (2013)
  online first</arxiv:comment>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1310.4689v1" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1310.4689v1" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/cond-mat/0611422v1</id>
    <updated>2006-11-16T08:22:26Z</updated>
    <published>2006-11-16T08:22:26Z</published>
    <title>Determination of the spatial TDR-sensor characteristics in strong
  dispersive subsoil using 3D-FEM frequency domain simulations in combination
  with microwave dielectric spectroscopy</title>
    <summary>  The spatial sensor characteristics of a 6cm TDR flat band cable sensor
section was simulated with finite element modelling (High Frequency Structure
Simulator-HFSS) under certain conditions: (i) in direct contact to the
surrounding material (air, water of different salinities, different synthetic
and natural soils (sand-silt-clay mixtures)), (ii) with consideration of a
defined gap of different size filled with air or water and (iii) the cable
sensor pressed at a borehole-wall. The complex dielectric permittivity or
complex electrical conductivity of the investigated saturated and unsaturated
soils was examined in the frequency range 50MHz-20GHz at room temperature and
atmospheric pressure with a HP8720D- network analyser. Three soil-specific
relaxation processes are assumed to act in the investigated
frequency-temperature-pressure range: one primary (main water relaxation) and
two secondary processes due to clay-water-ion interactions (bound water
relaxation and the Maxwell-Wagner effect). 3D finite element simulation is
performed with a 1/3 wavelength based adaptive mesh refinement at a solution
frequency of 1MHz, 10MHz, 0.1GHz, 1GHz and 12.5GHz. The electromagnetic field
distribution, S-parameter and step responses were examined.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Norman Wagner</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Eberhard Trinks</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Klaus Kupfer</name>
    </author>
    <arxiv:doi xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">10.1088/0957-0233/18/4/022</arxiv:doi>
    <link title="doi" href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1088/0957-0233/18/4/022" rel="related"/>
    <arxiv:comment xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">18 pages, 10 figures</arxiv:comment>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/cond-mat/0611422v1" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/cond-mat/0611422v1" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="cond-mat.mtrl-sci" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="cond-mat.mtrl-sci" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="cond-mat.other" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/physics/0503183v2</id>
    <updated>2005-10-13T09:03:28Z</updated>
    <published>2005-03-23T15:07:57Z</published>
    <title>Is the San Andreas Fracture a bayonet-shaped fracture as inferred from
  the acoustic body waves in the SAFOD Pilot hole ?</title>
    <summary>  The method using the propagation of acoustic body waves within the stress
modified areas around a vertical borehole has been applied to the granitic
formation penetrated by the SAFOD Pilot hole near the San Andreas Fault trace.
This method allows us investigating the horizontal in situ stresses. Only P
waves supplied useful and surprising information. A depth of 1270 m separates
an upper region of uniform thickness of stress modified areas, possibly
corresponding to a shear domain, and a lower region where there are
simultaneously two values of the thicknesses of the stress modified areas
(particularly between 1500 and 1600 m of depth) possibly corresponding to a
compressive and a shear domain. In order to integrate the contradictory effects
of the simultaneity of shear and compressive domains at some depths, as well as
the presence of three shear zones at particular depths, we propose that the San
Andreas Fault could be bayonet-shaped instead of planar. Other recent available
information in the literature about this fault, such as the presence of a fault
zone of low shear wave velocity, stress rotation measured with depth, and the
large angles of the frictional coefficients, can be logically explained by this
kind of fault geometry.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>André Rousseau</name>
      <arxiv:affiliation xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">OASU</arxiv:affiliation>
    </author>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/physics/0503183v2" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/physics/0503183v2" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/q-bio/0507004v1</id>
    <updated>2005-07-02T20:44:39Z</updated>
    <published>2005-07-02T20:44:39Z</published>
    <title>Life in solid ice</title>
    <summary>  Some microbes appear to be able to metabolize in glacial ice or permafrost.
The rate depends on temperature, nutrient level, and bioelement availability,
among other factors. I have developed a plausible argument that they do this
while confined in veins filled with acidic or saline solution that provides
nutrients and elements necessary for growth. Here I develop this scenario
further and discuss some of its implications for ice-covered planetary bodies
and for the the origin of life. An accompanying paper in the conference
proceedings (Bay et al.) discusses plans to test this hypothesis using
epifluorescence microscopy of pristine, unmelted ice samples and an optical
biospectrologging tool to assay living and dead microbes in boreholes in
glacial ice.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>P. Buford Price</name>
    </author>
    <arxiv:comment xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">21 pages, no figures, presented at Workshop on Life in Ancient Ice,
  June 30, 2001</arxiv:comment>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/q-bio/0507004v1" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/q-bio/0507004v1" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="q-bio.PE" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="q-bio.PE" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="q-bio.CB" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/0801.2308v1</id>
    <updated>2008-01-15T14:30:09Z</updated>
    <published>2008-01-15T14:30:09Z</published>
    <title>Monitoring field soil suction using a miniature tensiometer</title>
    <summary>  An experimental device was developed to monitor the field soil suction using
miniature tensiometer. This device consists of a double tube system that
ensures a good contact between the tensiometer and the soil surface at the
bottom of the testing borehole. This system also ensures the tensiometer
periodical retrieving without disturbing the surrounding soil. This device was
used to monitor the soil suction at the site of Boissy-le-Ch\^atel, France. The
measurement was performed at two depths (25 and 45 cm) during two months (May
and June 2004). The recorded suction data are analyzed by comparing with the
volumetric water content data recorded using TDR (Time Domain Reflectometer)
probes as well as the meteorological data. A good agreement between these
results was observed, showing a satisfactory performance of the developed
device.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Yu-Jun Cui</name>
      <arxiv:affiliation xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">ENPC-Cermes</arxiv:affiliation>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Anh-Minh Tang</name>
      <arxiv:affiliation xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">ENPC-Cermes</arxiv:affiliation>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Altin Theodore Mantho</name>
      <arxiv:affiliation xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">ENPC-Cermes</arxiv:affiliation>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Emmanuel De Laure</name>
      <arxiv:affiliation xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">ENPC-Cermes</arxiv:affiliation>
    </author>
    <arxiv:doi xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">10.1520/GTJ100769</arxiv:doi>
    <link title="doi" href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1520/GTJ100769" rel="related"/>
    <arxiv:journal_ref xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">Geotechnical Testing Journal 31, 1 (2008) 95-100</arxiv:journal_ref>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/0801.2308v1" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/0801.2308v1" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="physics.class-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.class-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/0806.2398v1</id>
    <updated>2008-06-14T19:38:58Z</updated>
    <published>2008-06-14T19:38:58Z</published>
    <title>Uncertainties and shortcomings of ground surface temperature histories
  derived from inversion of temperature logs</title>
    <summary>  Analysing borehole temperature data in terms of ground surface history can
add useful information to reconstructions of past climates. Therefore, a
rigorous assessment of uncertainties and error sources is a necessary
prerequisite for the meaningful interpretation of such ground surface
temperature histories. This study analyses the most prominent sources of
uncertainty. The diffusive nature of the process makes the inversion relatively
robust against incomplete knowledge of the thermal diffusivity. Similarly the
influence of heat production is small. It turns out that for investigations of
the last 1000 to 100000 years the maximum depth of the temperature log is
crucial. More than 3000 m are required for an optimal inversion.
Reconstructions of the last one or two millennia require only modestly deep
logs (&gt;300 m) but suffer severely from noisy data.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Andreas Hartmann</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Volker Rath</name>
    </author>
    <arxiv:doi xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">10.1088/1742-2132/2/4/S02</arxiv:doi>
    <link title="doi" href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1088/1742-2132/2/4/S02" rel="related"/>
    <arxiv:comment xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">28 pages, 18 figure, 3 tables</arxiv:comment>
    <arxiv:journal_ref xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">J. Geophys. Eng., 2, 299-311, 2005</arxiv:journal_ref>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/0806.2398v1" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/0806.2398v1" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.data-an" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/0908.4140v1</id>
    <updated>2009-08-28T06:38:31Z</updated>
    <published>2009-08-28T06:38:31Z</published>
    <title>Investigation of a hydraulic impact: a technology in rock breaking</title>
    <summary>  The finite element method and dimensional analysis have been applied in the
present paper to study a hydraulic impact, which is utilized in a non-explosive
rock breaking technology in mining industry. The impact process of a high speed
piston on liquid water, previously introduced in a borehole drilled in rock, is
numerically simulated. The research is focused on the influences of all the
parameters involved in the technology on the largest principal stress in the
rock, which is considered as one of the key factors to break the rock. Our
detailed parametric investigation reveals that the variation of the isotropic
rock material properties, especially its density, has no significant influence
on the largest principal stress. The influences of the depth of the hole and
the depth of the water column are also very small. On the other hand,
increasing the initial kinetic energy of the piston can dramatically increase
the largest principal stress and the best way to increase the initial kinetic
energy of the piston is to increase its initial velocity. Results from the
current dimensional analysis can be applied to optimize this non-explosive rock
breaking technology.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Martin Genet</name>
      <arxiv:affiliation xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">LMT</arxiv:affiliation>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Wenyi Yan</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Thanh Tran-Cong</name>
    </author>
    <arxiv:doi xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">10.1007/s00419-008-0256-z</arxiv:doi>
    <link title="doi" href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s00419-008-0256-z" rel="related"/>
    <arxiv:journal_ref xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">Archive of Applied Mechanics 79, 9 (2009) 825-841</arxiv:journal_ref>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/0908.4140v1" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/0908.4140v1" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="physics.class-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.class-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1010.2025v1</id>
    <updated>2010-10-11T08:01:44Z</updated>
    <published>2010-10-11T08:01:44Z</published>
    <title>Status and recent results of the South Pole Acoustic Test Setup</title>
    <summary>  The South Pole Acoustic Test Setup (SPATS) has been deployed to study the
feasibility of acoustic neutrino detection in Antarctic ice around the South
Pole. An array of four strings equipped with acoustic receivers and
transmitters, permanently installed in the upper 500 m of boreholes drilled for
the IceCube neutrino observatory, and a retrievable transmitter that can be
used in the water filled holes before the installation of the IceCube optical
strings are used to measure the ice acoustic properties. These include the
sound speed and its depth dependence, the attenuation length, the noise level,
and the rate and nature of transient background sources in the relevant
frequency range from 10 kHz to 100 kHz. SPATS is operating successfully since
January 2007 and has been able to either measure or constrain all parameters.
We present the latest results of SPATS and discuss their implications for
future acoustic neutrino detection activities in Antarctica.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Timo Karg</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>for the IceCube Collaboration</name>
    </author>
    <arxiv:doi xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">10.1016/j.nima.2010.10.122</arxiv:doi>
    <link title="doi" href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.nima.2010.10.122" rel="related"/>
    <arxiv:comment xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">7 pages, 5 figures, presented at the 4th International workshop on
  Acoustic and Radio EeV Neutrino detection Activities - ARENA 2010</arxiv:comment>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1010.2025v1" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1010.2025v1" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="astro-ph.IM" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="astro-ph.IM" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1202.0096v1</id>
    <updated>2012-02-01T04:37:54Z</updated>
    <published>2012-02-01T04:37:54Z</published>
    <title>Cross-Correlation Earthquake Precursors in the Hydrogeochemical and
  Geoacoustic Signals for the Kamchatka Peninsula</title>
    <summary>  We propose a new type of earthquake precursor based on the analysis of
correlation dynamics between geophysical signals of different nature. The
precursor is found using a two-parameter cross-correlation function introduced
within the framework of flicker-noise spectroscopy, a general statistical
physics approach to the analysis of time series. We consider an example of
cross-correlation analysis for water salinity time series, an integral
characteristic of the chemical composition of groundwater, and geoacoustic
emissions recorded at the G-1 borehole on the Kamchatka peninsula in the time
frame from 2001 to 2003, which is characterized by a sequence of three groups
of significant seismic events. We found that cross-correlation precursors took
place 27, 31, and 35 days ahead of the strongest earthquakes for each group of
seismic events, respectively. At the same time, precursory anomalies in the
signals themselves were observed only in the geoacoustic emissions for one
group of earthquakes.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>G. V. Ryabinin</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>V. A. Gavrilov</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Yu. S. Polyakov</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>S. F. Timashev</name>
    </author>
    <arxiv:doi xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">10.2478/s11600-012-0031-y</arxiv:doi>
    <link title="doi" href="http://dx.doi.org/10.2478/s11600-012-0031-y" rel="related"/>
    <arxiv:comment xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">21 pages, 5 figures, 1 table; to be published in "Acta Geophysica".
  arXiv admin note: substantial text overlap with arXiv:1101.1473</arxiv:comment>
    <arxiv:journal_ref xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">Acta Geophysica, 2012, Vol. 60, No. 3, pp. 874-893</arxiv:journal_ref>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1202.0096v1" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1202.0096v1" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.data-an" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1401.1092v1</id>
    <updated>2013-12-27T02:55:37Z</updated>
    <published>2013-12-27T02:55:37Z</published>
    <title>Bayesian compressive sensing for ultrawideband inverse scattering in
  random media</title>
    <summary>  We develop an ultrawideband (UWB) inverse scattering technique for
reconstructing continuous random media based on Bayesian compressive sensing.
In addition to providing maximum a posteriori estimates of the unknown weights,
Bayesian inversion provides estimate of the confidence level of the solution,
as well as a systematic approach for optimizing subsequent measurement(s) to
maximize information gain. We impose sparsity priors directly on spatial
harmonics to exploit the spatial correlation exhibited by continuous media, and
solve for their posterior probability density functions efficiently using a
fast relevance vector machine. We linearize the problem using the first-order
Born approximation which enables us to combine, in a single inversion,
measurements from multiple transmitters and ultrawideband frequencies. We
extend the method to high-contrast media using the distorted-Born iterative
method. We apply time-reversal strategies to adaptively focus the inversion
effort onto subdomains of interest, and hence reduce the overall inversion
cost. The proposed techniques are illustrated in a number of canonical
scenarios including crosshole and borehole sensing.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>A. E. Fouda</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>F. L. Teixeira</name>
    </author>
    <arxiv:doi xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">10.1088/0266-5611/30/11/114017</arxiv:doi>
    <link title="doi" href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1088/0266-5611/30/11/114017" rel="related"/>
    <arxiv:comment xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">29 pages, 10 figures</arxiv:comment>
    <arxiv:journal_ref xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">Inverse Problems, vol. 30, no. 11, 114017 (2014)</arxiv:journal_ref>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1401.1092v1" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1401.1092v1" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="physics.data-an" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.data-an" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1501.03081v1</id>
    <updated>2015-01-13T17:10:39Z</updated>
    <published>2015-01-13T17:10:39Z</published>
    <title>Noise-Produced Patterns in Images Constructed from Magnetic Flux Leakage
  Data</title>
    <summary>  Magnetic flux leakage measurements help identify the position, size and shape
of corrosion-related defects in steel casings used to protect boreholes drilled
into oil and gas reservoirs. Images constructed from magnetic flux leakage data
contain patterns related to noise inherent in the method. We investigate the
patterns and their scaling properties for the case of delta-correlated input
noise, and consider the implications for the method's ability to resolve
defects. The analytical evaluation of the noise-produced patterns is made
possible by model reduction facilitated by large-scale approximation. With
appropriate modification, the approach can be employed to analyze
noise-produced patterns in other situations where the data of interest are not
measured directly, but are related to the measured data by a complex linear
transform involving integrations with respect to spatial coordinates.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Anastasiya V. Pimenova</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Denis S. Goldobin</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Jeremy Levesley</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Peter Elkington</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Mark Bacciarelli</name>
    </author>
    <arxiv:doi xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">10.1051/mmnp/201510311</arxiv:doi>
    <link title="doi" href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1051/mmnp/201510311" rel="related"/>
    <arxiv:comment xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">11 pages, 2 figures</arxiv:comment>
    <arxiv:journal_ref xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">Math. Model. Nat. Phenom., vol. 10, no. 3, 139-148 (2015)</arxiv:journal_ref>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1501.03081v1" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1501.03081v1" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="physics.data-an" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.data-an" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="cond-mat.stat-mech" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1510.05292v1</id>
    <updated>2015-10-18T18:26:21Z</updated>
    <published>2015-10-18T18:26:21Z</published>
    <title>Muon tomography applied to active volcanoes</title>
    <summary>  Muon tomography is a generic imaging method using the differential absorption
of cosmic muons by matter. The measured contrast in the muons flux reflects the
matter density contrast as it does in conventional medical imaging. The
applications to volcanology present may advantadges induced by the features of
the target itself: limited access to dangerous zones, impossible use of
standard boreholes information, harsh environmental conditions etc. The
Diaphane project is one of the largest and leading collaboration in the field
and the present article summarizes recent results collected on the Lesser
Antilles, with a special emphasis on the Soufri\`ere of Guadeloupe.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Jacques Marteau</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Bruno Carlus</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Dominique Gibert</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Jean-Christophe Ianigro</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Kevin Jourde</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Bruno Kergosien</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Pascal Rolland</name>
    </author>
    <arxiv:comment xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">7 pages, 7 figures, International Conference on New
  Photo-detectors,PhotoDet2015, 6-9 July 2015, Moscow, Troitsk, Russia.
  Submitted to PoS</arxiv:comment>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1510.05292v1" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1510.05292v1" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="physics.ins-det" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.ins-det" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="hep-ex" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1701.00709v1</id>
    <updated>2017-01-03T14:53:41Z</updated>
    <published>2017-01-03T14:53:41Z</published>
    <title>Single-hole GPR reflection imaging of solute transport in a granitic
  aquifer</title>
    <summary>  Identifying transport pathways in fractured rock is extremely challenging as
flow is often organized in a few fractures that occupy a very small portion of
the rock volume. We demonstrate that saline tracer experiments combined with
single-hole ground penetrating radar (GPR) reflection imaging can be used to
monitor saline tracer movement within mm-aperture fractures. A dipole tracer
test was performed in a granitic aquifer by injecting a saline solution in a
known fracture, while repeatedly acquiring single-hole GPR sections in the
pumping borehole located 6 m away. The final depth-migrated difference sections
make it possible to identify consistent temporal changes over a 30 m depth
interval at locations corresponding to fractures previously imaged in GPR
sections acquired under natural flow and tracer-free conditions. The experiment
allows determining the dominant flow paths of the injected tracer and the
velocity (0.4-0.7 m/min) of the tracer front.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>C. Dorn</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>N- Linde</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>T. Le Borgne</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>O. Bour</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>L. Baron</name>
    </author>
    <arxiv:doi xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">10.1029/2011GL047152</arxiv:doi>
    <link title="doi" href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1029/2011GL047152" rel="related"/>
    <arxiv:journal_ref xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">Geophysical Research Letters, 38, L08401 (2011)</arxiv:journal_ref>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1701.00709v1" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1701.00709v1" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1705.03669v1</id>
    <updated>2017-05-10T09:27:16Z</updated>
    <published>2017-05-10T09:27:16Z</published>
    <title>Mind the Gap: A Well Log Data Analysis</title>
    <summary>  The main task in oil and gas exploration is to gain an understanding of the
distribution and nature of rocks and fluids in the subsurface. Well logs are
records of petro-physical data acquired along a borehole, providing direct
information about what is in the subsurface. The data collected by logging
wells can have significant economic consequences, due to the costs inherent to
drilling wells, and the potential return of oil deposits. In this paper, we
describe preliminary work aimed at building a general framework for well log
prediction.
  First, we perform a descriptive and exploratory analysis of the gaps in the
neutron porosity logs of more than a thousand wells in the North Sea. Then, we
generate artificial gaps in the neutron logs that reflect the statistics
collected before. Finally, we compare Artificial Neural Networks, Random
Forests, and three algorithms of Linear Regression in the prediction of missing
gaps on a well-by-well basis.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Rui L. Lopes</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Alípio Jorge</name>
    </author>
    <arxiv:comment xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">Part of DM4OG 2017 proceedings (arXiv:1705.03451)</arxiv:comment>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1705.03669v1" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1705.03669v1" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="cs.AI" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="cs.AI" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="stat.ML" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1706.03381v1</id>
    <updated>2017-06-11T17:31:14Z</updated>
    <published>2017-06-11T17:31:14Z</published>
    <title>A numerical method for efficient 3D inversions using Richards equation</title>
    <summary>  Fluid flow in the vadose zone is governed by Richards equation; it is
parameterized by hydraulic conductivity, which is a nonlinear function of
pressure head. Investigations in the vadose zone typically require
characterizing distributed hydraulic properties. Saturation or pressure head
data may include direct measurements made from boreholes. Increasingly, proxy
measurements from hydrogeophysics are being used to supply more spatially and
temporally dense data sets. Inferring hydraulic parameters from such datasets
requires the ability to efficiently solve and deterministically optimize the
nonlinear time domain Richards equation. This is particularly important as the
number of parameters to be estimated in a vadose zone inversion continues to
grow. In this paper, we describe an efficient technique to invert for
distributed hydraulic properties in 1D, 2D, and 3D. Our algorithm does not
store the Jacobian, but rather computes the product with a vector, which allows
the size of the inversion problem to become much larger than methods such as
finite difference or automatic differentiation; which are constrained by
computation and memory, respectively. We show our algorithm in practice for a
3D inversion of saturated hydraulic conductivity using saturation data through
time. The code to run our examples is open source and the algorithm presented
allows this inversion process to run on modest computational resources.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Rowan Cockett</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Lindsey J. Heagy</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Eldad Haber</name>
    </author>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1706.03381v1" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1706.03381v1" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1801.04351v1</id>
    <updated>2018-01-12T23:26:41Z</updated>
    <published>2018-01-12T23:26:41Z</published>
    <title>3D Cosmic Ray Muon Tomography from an Underground Tunnel</title>
    <summary>  We present an underground cosmic ray muon tomographic experiment imaging 3D
density of overburden, part of a joint study with differential gravity. Muon
data were acquired at four locations within a tunnel beneath Los Alamos, New
Mexico, and used in a 3D tomographic inversion to recover the spatial variation
in the overlying rock-air interface, and compared with a priori knowledge of
the topography. Densities obtained exhibit good agreement with preliminary
results of the gravity modeling, which will be presented elsewhere, and are
compatible with values reported in the literature. The modeled rock-air
interface matches that obtained from LIDAR within 4 m, our resolution, over
much of the model volume. This experiment demonstrates the power of cosmic ray
muons to image shallow geological targets using underground detectors, whose
development as borehole devices will be an important new direction of passive
geophysical imaging.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Elena Guardincerri</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Charlotte Rowe</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Emily Schultz-Fellenz</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Mousumi Roy</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Nicolas George</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Christopher Morris</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Jeffrey Bacon</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Matthew Durham</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Deborah Morley</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Kenie Plaud-Ramos</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Daniel Poulson</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Alain Bonneville</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Kouzes</name>
    </author>
    <arxiv:doi xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">10.1007/s00024-017-1526-x</arxiv:doi>
    <link title="doi" href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s00024-017-1526-x" rel="related"/>
    <arxiv:comment xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">17 pages, 8 figures</arxiv:comment>
    <arxiv:journal_ref xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">Pure and Applied Geophysics 174 (2017), 2133-2141</arxiv:journal_ref>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1801.04351v1" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1801.04351v1" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.app-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/hep-ex/0611050v1</id>
    <updated>2006-11-28T06:40:46Z</updated>
    <published>2006-11-28T06:40:46Z</published>
    <title>Q &amp; A Experiment to Search for Vacuum Dichroism, Pseudoscalar-Photon
  Interaction and Millicharged Fermions</title>
    <summary>  A number of experiments are underway to detect vacuum birefringence and
dichroism -- PVLAS, Q &amp; A, and BMV. Recently, PVLAS experiment has observed
optical rotation in vacuum by a magnetic field (vacuum dichroism). Theoretical
interpretations of this result include a possible pseudoscalar-photon
interaction and the existence of millicharged fermions. Here, we report the
progress and first results of Q &amp; A (QED [quantum electrodynamics] and Axion)
experiment proposed and started in 1994. A 3.5-m high-finesse (around 30,000)
Fabry-Perot prototype detector extendable to 7-m has been built and tested. We
use X-pendulums and automatic control schemes developed by the
gravitational-wave detection community for mirror suspension and cavity
control. To polarize the vacuum, we use a 2.3-T dipole permanent magnet, with
27-mm-diameter clear borehole and 0.6-m field length,. In the experiment, the
magnet is rotated at 5-10 rev/s to generate time-dependent polarization signal
with twice the rotation frequency. Our
ellipsometer/polarization-rotation-detection-system is formed by a pair of
Glan-Taylor type polarizing prisms with extinction ratio lower than 10-8
together with a polarization modulating Faraday Cell with/without a quarter
wave plate. We made an independent calibration of our apparatus by performing a
measurement of gaseous Cotton-Mouton effect of nitrogen. We present our first
experimental results and give a brief discussion of our experimental limit on
pseudo-scalar-photon interaction and millicharged fermions.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Sheng-Jui Chen</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Hsien-Hao Mei</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Wei-Tou Ni</name>
    </author>
    <arxiv:doi xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">10.1142/S0217732307025844</arxiv:doi>
    <link title="doi" href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1142/S0217732307025844" rel="related"/>
    <arxiv:comment xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">21 pages, 13 figures, submitted to Modern Physics Letters</arxiv:comment>
    <arxiv:journal_ref xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">Mod.Phys.Lett.A22:2815-2831,2007</arxiv:journal_ref>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/hep-ex/0611050v1" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/hep-ex/0611050v1" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="hep-ex" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="hep-ex" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="astro-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="gr-qc" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/physics/0312082v1</id>
    <updated>2003-12-12T02:34:50Z</updated>
    <published>2003-12-12T02:34:50Z</published>
    <title>Quantum Foam, Gravity and Gravitational Waves</title>
    <summary>  The new information-theoretic Process Physics has shown that space is a
quantum foam system with gravity being, in effect, an inhomogeneous in-flow of
the quantum foam into matter. The theory predicts that absolute motion with
respect to this system should be observable, and it is shown here that absolute
motion has been detected in at least seven experiments. As well this
experimental data also reveals the existence of a gravitational wave phenomena
associated with the in-flow. It is shown that Galilean Relativity and Special
Relativity are in fact compatible, contrary to current beliefs: absolute motion
actually causes the special relativity effects. The new theory of gravity
passes all the tests of the previous Newtonian and General Relativity theories,
but in addition resolves the numerous gravitational anomalies such as the
spiral galaxy `dark matter' effect, the absence of `dark matter' in elliptical
galaxies, the inconsistencies in measuring G, the borehole g anomaly, and
others. It is shown that Newtonian gravity is deeply flawed, because the solar
system from which it was developed has too high a spherical symmetry to have
revealed key aspects of the phenomena of gravity, and that General Relativity
inherited these flaws. The data are revealing that space has structure, and so
indicates for the first time evidence of quantum space and quantum gravity
effects.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Reginald T. Cahill</name>
      <arxiv:affiliation xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">Flinders University</arxiv:affiliation>
    </author>
    <arxiv:comment xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">60 pages, 22 eps figure files. To be published in Relativity,
  Gravitation, Cosmology</arxiv:comment>
    <arxiv:journal_ref xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">Relativity, Gravitation, Cosmology - New Developments, Nova
  Science, Ed. V. Dvoeglazov, 1-55, 2010</arxiv:journal_ref>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/physics/0312082v1" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/physics/0312082v1" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="physics.gen-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.gen-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/physics/0405147v2</id>
    <updated>2005-08-25T02:29:23Z</updated>
    <published>2004-05-28T04:16:52Z</published>
    <title>'Dark Matter' as a Quantum Foam In-Flow Effect</title>
    <summary>  The galactic `dark matter' effect is regarded as one of the major problems in
fundamental physics. Here it is explained as a self-interaction dynamical
effect of space itself, and so is not caused by an unknown form of matter.
Because it was based on Kepler's Laws for the motion of the planets in the
solar system the Newtonian theory of gravity was too restricted. A
reformulation and generalisation of the Newtonian theory of gravity in terms of
a velocity in-flow field, representing at a classical level the relative motion
of a quantum-foam substructure to space, reveals a key dynamical feature of the
phenomenon of gravity, namely the so called `dark matter' effect, which
manifests not only in spiral galaxy rotation curves, but also in the borehole g
anomaly, globular and galactic black holes, and in ongoing problems in
improving the accuracy with which Newton's gravitational constant G is
measured. The new theory of gravity involves an additional new dimensionless
gravitational constant, and experimental data reveals this to be the fine
structure constant. The new theory correctly predicts the globular cluster
black hole masses, and that the `frame-dragging' effect is caused by vorticity
in the in-flow. The relationship of the new theory of gravity to General
Relativity which, like Newtonian gravity, does not have the `dark matter'
dynamics, is explained.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Reginald T. Cahill</name>
      <arxiv:affiliation xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">Flinders University</arxiv:affiliation>
    </author>
    <arxiv:comment xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">46 pages, 8 figures. Figure 1 replaced</arxiv:comment>
    <arxiv:journal_ref xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">Trends in Dark Matter Research, ed. J. Val Blain, Nova Science
  Pub. NY 2005</arxiv:journal_ref>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/physics/0405147v2" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/physics/0405147v2" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="physics.gen-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.gen-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/physics/0602014v1</id>
    <updated>2006-02-02T08:10:42Z</updated>
    <published>2006-02-02T08:10:42Z</published>
    <title>Model of horizontal stress in the Aigion10 well (Corinth) calculated
  from acoustic body waves</title>
    <summary>  In this paper we try to deduce the in situ stresses from the monopole
acoustic waves of the well AIG10 between 689 and 1004 meters in depth (Corinth
Golf). This borehole crosses competent sedimentary formations (mainly
limestone), and the active Aigion fault between 769 and 780 meters in depth.
This study is the application of two methods previously described by the author
who shows the relationships between in situ horizontal stresses, and (i) the
presence or absence of double body waves, (ii) the amplitude ratios between S
and P waves (Rousseau, 2005a,b). The full waveforms of this well exhibit two
distinct domains separated by the Aigion fault. Within the upper area the three
typical waves (P, S and Stoneley) may appear, but the S waves are not numerous,
and there is no double body wave, whereas within the lower area there are
sometimes double P waves, but no S waves. From those observations, we conclude
that the stress domain is isotropic above the Aigion fault, and anisotropic
below, which is consistent with conclusions drawn by authors from other kinds
of data. The calculation applied to the characteristics of the double P waves
suggests that this horizontal stress anisotropy is very high, up to 190 % with
the maximum horizontal stress superior to 100 MPa and the minimum horizontal
stress close to zero at 939 meters in depth. The amplitude ratios between the S
and P wave indicate a very strong compression - which is isotropic - above the
Aigion fault.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>André Rousseau</name>
      <arxiv:affiliation xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">OASU</arxiv:affiliation>
    </author>
    <arxiv:comment xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">7 pages</arxiv:comment>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/physics/0602014v1" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/physics/0602014v1" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/0802.1931v1</id>
    <updated>2008-02-13T21:52:03Z</updated>
    <published>2008-02-13T21:52:03Z</published>
    <title>Petrophysical analysis of regional-scale thermal properties for improved
  simulations of geothermal installations and basin-scale heat and fluid flow</title>
    <summary>  Development of geothermal energy and basin-scale simulations of fluid and
heat flow both suffer from uncertain physical rock properties at depth.
Therefore, building better prognostic models are required. We analysed
hydraulic and thermal properties of the major rock types in the Molasse Basin
in Southern Germany. On about 400 samples thermal conductivity, density,
porosity, and sonic velocity were measured. Here, we propose a three-step
procedure with increasing complexity for analysis of the data set: First,
univariate descriptive statistics provides a general understanding of the data
structure, possibly still with large uncertainty. Examples show that the
remaining uncertainty can be as high as 0.8 W/(m K) or as low as 0.1 W/(m K).
This depends on the possibility to subdivide the geologic units into data sets
that are also petrophysically similar. Then, based on all measurements,
cross-plot and quick-look methods are used to gain more insight into
petrophysical relationships and to refine the analysis. Because these measures
usually imply an exactly determined system they do not provide strict error
bounds. The final, most complex step comprises a full inversion of select
subsets of the data comprising both laboratory and borehole measurements. The
example presented shows the possibility to refine the used mixing laws for
Petrophysical properties and the estimation of mineral properties. These can be
estimated to an accuracy of 0.3 W/(m K). The predictive errors for the
measurements are 0.07 W/(m K), 70 m/s, and 8 kg/m^3 for thermal conductivity,
sonic velocity, and bulk density, respectively.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Andreas Hartmann</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Renate Pechnig</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Christoph Clauser</name>
    </author>
    <arxiv:doi xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">10.1007/s00531-007-0283-y</arxiv:doi>
    <link title="doi" href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s00531-007-0283-y" rel="related"/>
    <arxiv:comment xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">13 pages, 10 figures, International Journal of Earth Sciences</arxiv:comment>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/0802.1931v1" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/0802.1931v1" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.data-an" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1410.6106v1</id>
    <updated>2014-10-22T16:40:34Z</updated>
    <published>2014-10-22T16:40:34Z</published>
    <title>BlackSeaHazNet Scientific Report - EU FP7 IRSES project 2011-2014</title>
    <summary>  The aims of the project 2011-2014) are in the project title- Complex Research
of Earthquakes Forecasting Possibilities, Seismic and Climate Change
Correlations- to create a team for researching the above mentioned problem. In
the Project participated 76 scientists from 16 Institutes and 8 countries-
Armenia, Bulgaria, Georgia, Greece, Macedonia, Slovenia, Turkey and Ukraine.
The main results are shortly listed in the next. Creating a group which is able
to fulfill a Complex Research of Earthquakes Forecasting Possibilities; The
main result is statistical prove of imminent forecasting possibility for
seismic regional activity on the basis of the geomagnetic monitoring in the
framework of special created data acquisition system for earthquakes archiving,
visualization and analysis (geomagnetic quake approach). Illustrated with the
data from INTERMAGNET stations- PAG (Panagurichte, Bulgaria), SUA (Surlari,
Romania), GCK (Grocka, Serbia) and LAquila (AQU, Italy) for the last 5-8 years;
The application of the geomagnetic quake approach for analysis of boreholes
water level demonstrated that the water level variation is also a reliable
imminent regional earthquakes precursor; It was formulated and researched the
hypothesis for reality of Climate change Seismic correlation and axion- geo
-nuclear -reactors existence; The research of deep Earth crust structure and
upper mantle study using the inverse problem analysis of the Earth
electromagnetic radiation in radio diapason, measured with Astrogon device was
performed in Greece and Bulgaria; The members of Project participated many
International Conferences, Congresses and Workshops with presentations and
published many 97 papers.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Strachimir Cht. Mavrodiev</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Natalia Kilifarska</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Lazo Pekevski</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Giorgi Kikuashvili</name>
    </author>
    <arxiv:comment xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">23 pages, 17 figures</arxiv:comment>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1410.6106v1" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1410.6106v1" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1602.00152v2</id>
    <updated>2016-08-02T05:54:19Z</updated>
    <published>2016-01-30T19:16:14Z</published>
    <title>Imminent earthquake forecasting on the basis of Japan INTERMAGNET
  stations, NEIC, NOAA and Tide code data analysis</title>
    <summary>  This research presents one possible way for imminent prediction of earthquake
magnitude, depth and epicenter coordinates by solving the inverse problem using
a data acquisition network system for monitoring, archiving and complex
analysis of geophysical variables precursors. Among many possible precursors
the most reliable are the geoelectromagnetic field, the boreholes water level,
the radon surface concentration, the local heat flow, the ionosphere variables,
the low frequency atmosphere and Earth core waves. In this study only
geomagnetic data are used. Within the framework of geomagnetic quake approach
it is possible to perform an imminent regional seismic activity forecasting on
the basis of simple analysis of geomagnetic data which use a new variable Schtm
with dimension surface density of energy. Such analysis of Memambetsu, Kakioka,
Kanoya (Japan, INTERMAGNET) stations and NEIC earthquakes data, the hypothesis
that the predicted earthquake is this with bigest value of the variable Schtm
permit to formulate an inverse problem (overdetermined algebraic system) for
precursors signals like a functions of earthquake magnitude, depth and distance
from a monitoring point. Thus, in the case of data acquisition network system
existence, which includes monitoring of more than one reliable precursor
variables in at least four points distributed within the area with a radius of
up to 700 km, there will be enough algebraic equations for calculation of
impending earthquake magnitude, depth and distance, solving the overdetermined
algebraic system.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>S. Cht. Mavrodiev</name>
    </author>
    <arxiv:doi xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">10.4236/ojer.2016.51005.</arxiv:doi>
    <link title="doi" href="http://dx.doi.org/10.4236/ojer.2016.51005." rel="related"/>
    <arxiv:comment xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">21 pages, 14 figures, 2 tables</arxiv:comment>
    <arxiv:journal_ref xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">Open Journal of Earthquake Research, 5, 62-78</arxiv:journal_ref>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1602.00152v2" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1602.00152v2" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1509.07074v1</id>
    <updated>2015-09-23T17:48:24Z</updated>
    <published>2015-09-23T17:48:24Z</published>
    <title>Quantification of sand fraction from seismic attributes using
  Neuro-Fuzzy approach</title>
    <summary>  In this paper, we illustrate the modeling of a reservoir property (sand
fraction) from seismic attributes namely seismic impedance, seismic amplitude,
and instantaneous frequency using Neuro-Fuzzy (NF) approach. Input dataset
includes 3D post-stacked seismic attributes and six well logs acquired from a
hydrocarbon field located in the western coast of India. Presence of thin sand
and shale layers in the basin area makes the modeling of reservoir
characteristic a challenging task. Though seismic data is helpful in
extrapolation of reservoir properties away from boreholes; yet, it could be
challenging to delineate thin sand and shale reservoirs using seismic data due
to its limited resolvability. Therefore, it is important to develop
state-of-art intelligent methods for calibrating a nonlinear mapping between
seismic data and target reservoir variables. Neural networks have shown its
potential to model such nonlinear mappings; however, uncertainties associated
with the model and datasets are still a concern. Hence, introduction of Fuzzy
Logic (FL) is beneficial for handling these uncertainties. More specifically,
hybrid variants of Artificial Neural Network (ANN) and fuzzy logic, i.e., NF
methods, are capable for the modeling reservoir characteristics by integrating
the explicit knowledge representation power of FL with the learning ability of
neural networks. The documented results in this study demonstrate acceptable
resemblance between target and predicted variables, and hence, encourage the
application of integrated machine learning approaches such as Neuro-Fuzzy in
reservoir characterization domain. Furthermore, visualization of the variation
of sand probability in the study area would assist in identifying placement of
potential wells for future drilling operations.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Akhilesh K Verma</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Soumi Chaki</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Aurobinda Routray</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>William K Mohanty</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Mamata Jenamani</name>
    </author>
    <arxiv:doi xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">10.1016/j.jappgeo.2014.10.005</arxiv:doi>
    <link title="doi" href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jappgeo.2014.10.005" rel="related"/>
    <arxiv:comment xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">Journal of Applied Geophysics, volume 111, page 141-155</arxiv:comment>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1509.07074v1" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1509.07074v1" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="cs.CE" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="cs.CE" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="cs.AI" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1607.05128v1</id>
    <updated>2016-07-07T19:20:16Z</updated>
    <published>2016-07-07T19:20:16Z</published>
    <title>Modeling cross-hole slug tests in an unconfined aquifer</title>
    <summary>  A modified version of a published slug test model for unconfined aquifers is
applied to cross-hole slug test data collected in field tests conducted at the
Widen site in Switzerland. The model accounts for water-table effects using the
linearised kinematic condition. The model also accounts for inertial effects in
source and observation wells. The primary objective of this work is to
demonstrate applicability of this semi-analytical model to multi-well and
multi-level pneumatic slug tests. The pneumatic perturbation was applied at
discrete intervals in a source well and monitored at discrete vertical
intervals in observation wells. The source and observation well pairs were
separated by distances of up to 4 m. The analysis yielded vertical profiles of
hydraulic conductivity, specific storage, and specific yield at observation
well locations. The hydraulic parameter estimates are compared to results from
prior pumping and single-well slug tests conducted at the site, as well as to
estimates from particle size analyses of sediment collected from boreholes
during well installation. The results are in general agreement with results
from prior tests and are indicative of a sand and gravel aquifer. Sensitivity
analysis show that model identification of specific yield is strongest at
late-time. However, the usefulness of late-time data is limited due to the low
signal-to-noise ratios.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Bwalya Malama</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Kristopher L. Kuhlman</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Ralf Brauchler</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Peter Bayer</name>
    </author>
    <arxiv:doi xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">10.1016/j.jhydrol.2016.06.060</arxiv:doi>
    <link title="doi" href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jhydrol.2016.06.060" rel="related"/>
    <arxiv:comment xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">6 figures, 2 tables</arxiv:comment>
    <arxiv:journal_ref xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">Journal of Hydrology, Volume 540, September 2016, Pages 784-796</arxiv:journal_ref>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1607.05128v1" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1607.05128v1" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1611.00867v1</id>
    <updated>2016-11-03T03:06:57Z</updated>
    <published>2016-11-03T03:06:57Z</published>
    <title>Bio-inspired seismic metamaterials: Time domain simulations in
  transformed crystals</title>
    <summary>  We introduce the concept of transformation crystallography which consists of
the application of geometric transforms to periodic structures. We consider
motifs with three-fold, four-fold and six-fold symmetries according to the
crystallographic restriction theorem. Furthermore, we define motifs with
five-fold symmetry such as quasi-crystals generated by a cut-and-projection
method. We analyze elastic wave propagation in the transformed crystals and
(Penrose-type) quasi-crystals with the finite difference time domain freeware
SimSonic. We consider geometric transforms underpinning the design of seismic
cloaks with square, circular, elliptical and peanut shapes in the context of
triangular, square and honeycomb crystals. Interestingly, the use of morphing
techniques leads to the design of cloaks with interpolated geometries
reminiscent of Victor Vasarely's artwork. Employing the case of transformed
graphene-like (honeycomb) structures allows one to draw useful analogies
between large-scale seismic metamaterials such as soils structured with columns
of concrete or grout with soil and nanoscale biochemical metamaterials. We
further point out similarities between cloaks for elastodynamic and
hydrodynamic waves and cloaks for diffusion (heat or mass) diffusion processes,
notably with respect to invisibility and protection. Experimental data
extracted from field test analysis of soil structured with boreholes
demonstrates the application of bio-inspired seismic metamaterials. We conclude
that these novel materials hold strong applications in biophysics and
geophysics.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Ronald Aznavourian</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Tania Puvirajesinghe</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Stephane Brule</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Stefan Enoch</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Sebastien Guenneau</name>
    </author>
    <arxiv:comment xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">25 pages, 14 figures</arxiv:comment>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1611.00867v1" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1611.00867v1" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="physics.bio-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.bio-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1701.01351v1</id>
    <updated>2017-01-05T15:28:43Z</updated>
    <published>2017-01-05T15:28:43Z</published>
    <title>Hydrogeophysical characterization of transport processes in fractured
  rock by combining push-pull tracer tests and single-hole ground penetrating
  radar</title>
    <summary>  The in situ characterization of transport processes in fractured media is
particularly challenging due to the considerable spatial uncertainty on tracer
pathways and dominant controlling processes, such as dispersion, channeling,
trapping, matrix diffusion, ambient and density driven flows. We attempted to
reduce this uncertainty by coupling push-pull tracer experiments with
single-hole ground penetrating radar (GPR) time-lapse imaging. The experiments
involved different injection fractures, chaser volumes and resting times, and
were performed at the fractured rock research site of Ploemeur in France (H+
network, hplus.ore.fr/en). For the GPR acquisitions, we used both fixed and
moving antenna setups in a borehole that was isolated with a flexible liner.
During the fixed-antenna experiment, time-varying GPR reflections allowed us to
track the spatial and temporal dynamics of the tracer during the push-pull
experiment. During the moving antenna experiments, we clearly imaged the
dominant fractures in which tracer transport took place, fractures in which the
tracer was trapped for longer time periods, and the spatial extent of the
tracer distribution (up to 8 m) at different times. This demonstrated the
existence of strongly channelized flow in the first few meters and radial flow
at greater distances. By varying the resting time of a given experiment, we
identified regions affected by density-driven and ambient flow. These
experiments open up new perspectives for coupled hydrogeophysical inversion
aimed at understanding transport phenomena in fractured rock formations.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>A. Shakas</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>N. Linde</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>L. Baron</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>O. Bochet</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name> T.</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>O. Bour</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Le Borgne</name>
    </author>
    <arxiv:doi xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">10.1002/2015WR017837</arxiv:doi>
    <link title="doi" href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/2015WR017837" rel="related"/>
    <arxiv:journal_ref xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">Water Resources Research (2016), 52, 938-953</arxiv:journal_ref>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1701.01351v1" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1701.01351v1" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1203.6539v3</id>
    <updated>2012-07-15T15:09:34Z</updated>
    <published>2012-03-29T14:44:05Z</published>
    <title>Regularization strategy for the layered inversion of airborne TEM data:
  application to VTEM data acquired over the basin of Franceville (Gabon)</title>
    <summary>  Airborne transient electromagnetic (TEM) is a cost-effective method to image
the distribution of electrical conductivity in the ground. We consider layered
earth inversion to interpret large data sets of hundreds of kilometre.
Different strategies can be used to solve this inverse problem. This consists
in managing the a priori information to avoid the mathematical instability and
provide the most plausible model of conductivity in depth. In order to obtain
fast and realistic inversion program, we tested three kinds of regularization:
two are based on standard Tikhonov procedure which consist in minimizing not
only the data misfit function but a balanced optimization function with
additional terms constraining the lateral and the vertical smoothness of the
conductivity; another kind of regularization is based on reducing the condition
number of the kernel by changing the layout of layers before minimizing the
data misfit function. Finally, in order to get a more realistic distribution of
conductivity, notably by removing negative conductivity values, we suggest an
additional recursive filter based upon the inversion of the logarithm of the
conductivity. All these methods are tested on synthetic and real data sets.
Synthetic data have been calculated by 2.5D modelling; they are used to
demonstrate that these methods provide equivalent quality in terms of data
misfit and accuracy of the resulting image; the limit essentially comes on
special targets with sharp 2D geometries. The real data case is from
Helicopter-borne TEM data acquired in the basin of Franceville (Gabon) where
borehole conductivity loggings are used to show the good accuracy of the
inverted models in most areas, and some biased depths in areas where strong
lateral changes may occur.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Julien Guillemoteau</name>
      <arxiv:affiliation xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">IPGS</arxiv:affiliation>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Pascal Sailhac</name>
      <arxiv:affiliation xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">IPGS</arxiv:affiliation>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Mickael Behaegel</name>
      <arxiv:affiliation xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">IPGS</arxiv:affiliation>
    </author>
    <arxiv:doi xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">10.1111/j.1365-2478.2011.00990.x</arxiv:doi>
    <link title="doi" href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-2478.2011.00990.x" rel="related"/>
    <arxiv:journal_ref xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">Geophysical Prospecting 59, 6 (2011) 1132-1143</arxiv:journal_ref>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1203.6539v3" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1203.6539v3" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1406.7440v2</id>
    <updated>2014-07-06T12:47:13Z</updated>
    <published>2014-06-28T21:09:06Z</published>
    <title>Why Fracking Works and How to Optimize It</title>
    <summary>  Although spectacular advances in hydraulic fracturing, aka fracking, have
taken place and many aspects are well understood by now, the topology, geometry
and evolution of the crack system hydraulically produced in the shale still
remains an enigma. Expert opinions differ widely and fracture mechanicians must
wonder why fracking works. Fracture mechanics of individual pressurized cracks
has recently been clarified but the vital problem of stability of interacting
hydraulic cracks escaped attention. Progress in this regard would likely allow
optimization of fracking and reduction of environmental footprint. The present
article first focuses on the classical solutions of the critical states of
localization instability of a system of cooling or shrinkage cracks and shows
that these solutions can be transferred to the system of hydraulic cracks. It
is concluded that if the profile of hydraulic pressure along the cracks can be
made almost uniform, with a steep pressure drop at the front, the localization
instability can be avoided. To achieve this kind of profile the pumping rate
(corrected for the leak rate) must not be too high. Subsequently, numerical
solutions are presented to show that an idealized system of circular
equidistant vertical cracks propagating from a horizontal borehole behaves
similarly. It is pointed out that one important role of proppants, as well as
acids that promote creation debris in the new cracks, is that they partially
help to limit crack closings and thus localization. Based on the extremely low
permeability of gas shale, one must imagine a hierarchical progressively
refined crack systems in which the finest cracks have spacing in the
sub-centimeter range. The overall conclusion is that what makes fracking work
is the suppression or mitigation of localization instabilities of crack
systems, which requires achieving uniform pressure profiles along the cracks.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Z. P. Bazant</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>M. Salviato</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>V. T. Chau</name>
    </author>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1406.7440v2" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1406.7440v2" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1103.1216v2</id>
    <updated>2011-10-18T08:22:24Z</updated>
    <published>2011-03-07T09:31:49Z</published>
    <title>Background studies for acoustic neutrino detection at the South Pole</title>
    <summary>  The detection of acoustic signals from ultra-high energy neutrino
interactions is a promising method to measure the tiny flux of cosmogenic
neutrinos expected on Earth. The energy threshold for this process depends
strongly on the absolute noise level in the target material. The South Pole
Acoustic Test Setup (SPATS), deployed in the upper part of four boreholes of
the IceCube Neutrino Observatory, has monitored the noise in Antarctic ice at
the geographic South Pole for more than two years down to 500 m depth. The
noise is very stable and Gaussian distributed. Lacking an in-situ calibration
up to now, laboratory measurements have been used to estimate the absolute
noise level in the 10 to 50 kHz frequency range to be smaller than 20 mPa.
Using a threshold trigger, sensors of the South Pole Acoustic Test Setup
registered acoustic pulse-like events in the IceCube detector volume and its
vicinity. Acoustic signals from refreezing IceCube holes and from anthropogenic
sources have been used to localize acoustic events. Monte Carlo simulations of
sound propagating from the established sources to the SPATS sensors have
allowed to check corresponding model expectations. An upper limit on the
neutrino flux at energies $E_\nu &gt; 10^{11}$ GeV is derived from acoustic data
taken over eight months.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name> The IceCube Collaboration</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>R. Abbasi</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Y. Abdou</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>T. Abu-Zayyad</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>J. Adams</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>J. A. Aguilar</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>M. Ahlers</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>K. Andeen</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>J. Auffenberg</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>X. Bai</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>M. Baker</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>S. W. Barwick</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>R. Bay</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>J. L. Bazo Alba</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>K. Beattie</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>J. J. Beatty</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>S. Bechet</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>J. K. Becker</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>K. -H. Becker</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>M. L. Benabderrahmane</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>S. BenZvi</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>J. Berdermann</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>P. Berghaus</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>D. Berley</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>E. Bernardini</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>D. Bertrand</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>D. Z. Besson</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>D. Bindig</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>M. Bissok</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>E. Blaufuss</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>J. Blumenthal</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>D. J. Boersma</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>C. Bohm</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>D. Bose</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>S. Böser</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>O. Botner</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>J. Braun</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>A. M. Brown</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>S. Buitink</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>M. Carson</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>D. Chirkin</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>B. Christy</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>J. Clem</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>F. Clevermann</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>S. Cohen</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>C. Colnard</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>D. F. Cowen</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>M. V. D'Agostino</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>M. Danninger</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>J. Daughhetee</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>J. C. Davis</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>C. De Clercq</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>L. Demirörs</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>T. Denger</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>O. Depaepe</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>F. Descamps</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>P. Desiati</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>G. de Vries-Uiterweerd</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>T. DeYoung</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>J. C. Diaz-Vélez</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>M. Dierckxsens</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>J. Dreyer</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>J. P. Dumm</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>R. Ehrlich</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>J. Eisch</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>R. W. Ellsworth</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>O. Engdegård</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>S. Euler</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>P. A. Evenson</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>O. Fadiran</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>A. R. Fazely</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>A. Fedynitch</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>T. Feusels</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>K. Filimonov</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>C. Finley</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>T. Fischer-Wasels</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>M. M. Foerster</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>B. D. Fox</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>A. Franckowiak</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>R. Franke</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>T. K. Gaisser</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>J. Gallagher</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>M. Geisler</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>L. Gerhardt</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>L. Gladstone</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>T. Glüsenkamp</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>A. Goldschmidt</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>J. A. Goodman</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>D. Grant</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>T. Griesel</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>A. Groß</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>S. Grullon</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>M. Gurtner</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>C. Ha</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>A. Hallgren</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>F. Halzen</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>K. Han</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>K. Hanson</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>D. Heinen</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>K. Helbing</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>P. Herquet</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>S. Hickford</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>G. C. Hill</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>K. D. Hoffman</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>A. Homeier</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>K. Hoshina</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>D. Hubert</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>W. Huelsnitz</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>J. -P. Hülß</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>P. O. Hulth</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>K. Hultqvist</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>S. Hussain</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>A. Ishihara</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>J. Jacobsen</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>G. S. Japaridze</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>H. Johansson</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>J. M. Joseph</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>K. -H. Kampert</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>A. Kappes</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>T. Karg</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>A. Karle</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>J. L. Kelley</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>P. Kenny</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>J. Kiryluk</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>F. Kislat</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>S. R. Klein</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>J. -H. Köhne</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>G. Kohnen</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>H. Kolanoski</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>L. Köpke</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>S. Kopper</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>D. J. Koskinen</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>M. Kowalski</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>T. Kowarik</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>M. Krasberg</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>T. Krings</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>G. Kroll</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>K. Kuehn</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>T. Kuwabara</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>M. Labare</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>S. Lafebre</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>K. Laihem</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>H. Landsman</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>M. J. Larson</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>R. Lauer</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>J. Lünemann</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>J. Madsen</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>P. Majumdar</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>A. Marotta</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>R. Maruyama</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>K. Mase</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>H. S. Matis</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>K. Meagher</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>M. Merck</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>P. Mészáros</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>T. Meures</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>E. Middell</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>N. Milke</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>J. Miller</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>T. Montaruli</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>R. Morse</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>S. M. Movit</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>R. Nahnhauer</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>J. W. Nam</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>U. Naumann</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>P. Nießen</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>D. R. Nygren</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>S. Odrowski</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>A. Olivas</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>M. Olivo</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>A. O'Murchadha</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>M. Ono</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>S. Panknin</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>L. Paul</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>C. Pérez de los Heros</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>J. Petrovic</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>A. Piegsa</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>D. Pieloth</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>R. Porrata</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>J. Posselt</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>P. B. Price</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>M. Prikockis</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>G. T. Przybylski</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>K. Rawlins</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>P. Redl</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>E. Resconi</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>W. Rhode</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>M. Ribordy</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>A. Rizzo</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>J. P. Rodrigues</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>P. Roth</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>F. Rothmaier</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>C. Rott</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>T. Ruhe</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>D. Rutledge</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>B. Ruzybayev</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>D. Ryckbosch</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>H. -G. Sander</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>M. Santander</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>S. Sarkar</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>K. Schatto</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>T. Schmidt</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>A. Schönwald</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>A. Schukraft</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>A. Schultes</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>O. Schulz</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>M. Schunck</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>D. Seckel</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>B. Semburg</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>S. H. Seo</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Y. Sestayo</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>S. Seunarine</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>A. Silvestri</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>A. Slipak</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>G. M. Spiczak</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>C. Spiering</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>M. Stamatikos</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>T. Stanev</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>G. Stephens</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>T. Stezelberger</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>R. G. Stokstad</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>A. Stössl</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>S. Stoyanov</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>E. A. Strahler</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>T. Straszheim</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>M. Stür</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>G. W. Sullivan</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Q. Swillens</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>H. Taavola</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>I. Taboada</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>A. Tamburro</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>A. Tepe</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>S. Ter-Antonyan</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>S. Tilav</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>P. A. Toale</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>S. Toscano</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>D. Tosi</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>D. Turčan</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>N. van Eijndhoven</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>J. Vandenbroucke</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>A. Van Overloop</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>J. van Santen</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>M. Vehring</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>M. Voge</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>C. Walck</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>T. Waldenmaier</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>M. Wallraff</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>M. Walter</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Ch. Weaver</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>C. Wendt</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>S. Westerhoff</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>N. Whitehorn</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>K. Wiebe</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>C. H. Wiebusch</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>D. R. Williams</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>R. Wischnewski</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>H. Wissing</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>M. Wolf</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>K. Woschnagg</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>C. Xu</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>X. W. Xu</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>J. P. Yanez</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>G. Yodh</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>S. Yoshida</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>P. Zarzhitsky</name>
    </author>
    <arxiv:doi xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">10.1016/j.astropartphys.2011.09.004</arxiv:doi>
    <link title="doi" href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.astropartphys.2011.09.004" rel="related"/>
    <arxiv:comment xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">17 pages, 14 figures</arxiv:comment>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1103.1216v2" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1103.1216v2" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="astro-ph.IM" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="astro-ph.IM" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
