<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <link href="http://arxiv.org/api/query?search_query%3Dall%3Awellbore%26id_list%3D%26start%3D0%26max_results%3D2000" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <title type="html">ArXiv Query: search_query=all:wellbore&amp;id_list=&amp;start=0&amp;max_results=2000</title>
  <id>http://arxiv.org/api/hpALIzzqX/OA/uxXL1Syw+XZ9n0</id>
  <updated>2018-03-02T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
  <opensearch:totalResults xmlns:opensearch="http://a9.com/-/spec/opensearch/1.1/">6</opensearch:totalResults>
  <opensearch:startIndex xmlns:opensearch="http://a9.com/-/spec/opensearch/1.1/">0</opensearch:startIndex>
  <opensearch:itemsPerPage xmlns:opensearch="http://a9.com/-/spec/opensearch/1.1/">2000</opensearch:itemsPerPage>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1212.2763v1</id>
    <updated>2012-12-12T10:34:18Z</updated>
    <published>2012-12-12T10:34:18Z</published>
    <title>Thermal Fracturing of Geothermal Wells and the Effects of Borehole
  Orientation</title>
    <summary>  An enhanced geothermal system (EGS) expands the potential of geothermal
energy by enabling the exploitation of regions that lack conventional
hydrothermal resources. The EGS subsurface system is created by engineering
enhanced flow paths between injection and production wells. Hydraulic
stimulation of existing fracture networks has been successfully achieved for
unconventional geothermal resources. More recently proposed concepts increase
the use of drilled wellbores in hard rock to connect the injection and
production wells. The present work investigates the long-term thermal effects
of deviated geothermal wellbores and studies how the cooling of the borehole
wall results in thermally induced tensile fractures. The results show that
induced fractures are created by a combination of in situ and thermal stresses,
and that the extent to which thermally induced tensile wall fractures are
created largely depends on how the wellbores are oriented with respect to the
pre-existing stresses of the reservoir. If the system is not optimized with
respect to in situ stresses, the risk of wellbore instability becomes severe
within less than a year of production. In contrast, if the orientation of the
wellbores is optimized, thermally induced instabilities can be completely
excluded as potential risks for the operational lifetime of the system.
Furthermore, our results show that the thermal failure process strongly depends
on the temperature of the injected water but is only weakly affected by the
injection rate.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Kjetil M. D. Hals</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Inga Berre</name>
    </author>
    <arxiv:comment xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">10 pages, 5 figures, submitted to Geothermics</arxiv:comment>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1212.2763v1" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1212.2763v1" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="cond-mat.mtrl-sci" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.flu-dyn" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1110.5940v2</id>
    <updated>2011-10-28T17:08:36Z</updated>
    <published>2011-10-26T22:18:40Z</published>
    <title>Unified Analytical Solution for Radial Flow to a Well in a Confined
  Aquifer</title>
    <summary>  Drawdowns generated by extracting water from a large diameter (e.g. water
supply) well are affected by wellbore storage. We present an analytical
solution in Laplace transformed space for drawdown in a uniform anisotropic
aquifer caused by withdrawing water at a constant rate from a partially
penetrating well with storage. The solution is back transformed into the time
domain numerically. When the pumping well is fully penetrating our solution
reduces to that of Papadopulos and Cooper [1967]; Hantush [1964] when the
pumping well has no wellbore storage; Theis [1935] when both conditions are
fulfilled and Yang et.al. [2006] when the pumping well is partially
penetrating, has finite radius but lacks storage. We use our solution to
explore graphically the effects of partial penetration, wellbore storage and
anisotropy on time evolutions of drawdown in the pumping well and in
observation wells.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Phoolendra Kumar Mishra</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Velimir V. Vesselinov</name>
    </author>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1110.5940v2" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1110.5940v2" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="math-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="math-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="math.MP" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1509.05812v1</id>
    <updated>2015-09-18T22:08:55Z</updated>
    <published>2015-09-18T22:08:55Z</published>
    <title>Development of configurational forces during the injection of an elastic
  rod</title>
    <summary>  When an inextensible elastic rod is 'injected' through a sliding sleeve
against a fixed constraint, configurational forces are developed, deeply
influencing the mechanical response. This effect, which is a consequence of the
change in length of the portion of the rod included between the sliding sleeve
and the fixed constraint, is theoretically demonstrated (via integration of the
elastica) and experimentally validated on a proof-of-concept structure
(displaying an interesting force reversal in the load/deflection diagram), to
provide conclusive evidence to mechanical phenomena relevant in several
technologies, including guide wire for artery catheterization, or wellbore
insertion of a steel pipe.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>F. Bosi</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>D. Misseroni</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>F. Dal Corso</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>D. Bigoni</name>
    </author>
    <arxiv:doi xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">10.1016/j.eml.2015.04.007</arxiv:doi>
    <link title="doi" href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.eml.2015.04.007" rel="related"/>
    <arxiv:comment xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">10 pages, 4 figures, Extreme Mechanics Letters (2015)</arxiv:comment>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1509.05812v1" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1509.05812v1" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="cond-mat.soft" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="cond-mat.soft" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1111.1265v2</id>
    <updated>2012-03-06T00:29:20Z</updated>
    <published>2011-11-04T22:14:22Z</published>
    <title>Saturated-Unsaturated flow in a Compressible Leaky-unconfined Aquifer</title>
    <summary>  An analytical solution is developed for three-dimensional flow towards a
partially penetrating large-diameter well in an unconfined aquifer bounded
below by an aquitard of finite or semi-infinite extent. The analytical solution
is derived using Laplace and Hankel transforms, then inverted numerically.
Existing solutions for flow in leaky unconfined aquifers neglect the
unsaturated zone following an assumption of instantaneous drainage assumption
due to Neuman [1972]. We extend the theory of leakage in unconfined aquifers by
(1) including water flow and storage in the unsaturated zone above the water
table, and (2) allowing the finite-diameter pumping well to partially penetrate
the aquifer. The investigation of model-predicted results shows that leakage
from an underlying aquitard leads to significant departure from the unconfined
solution without leakage. The investigation of dimensionless time-drawdown
relationships shows that the aquitard drawdown also depends on unsaturated zone
properties and the pumping-well wellbore storage effects.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Phoolendra K. Mishra</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Velimir V. Vessilinov</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Kristopher L. Kuhlman</name>
    </author>
    <arxiv:doi xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">10.1016/j.advwatres.2012.03.007</arxiv:doi>
    <link title="doi" href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.advwatres.2012.03.007" rel="related"/>
    <arxiv:journal_ref xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">AWR-11-418 2012</arxiv:journal_ref>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1111.1265v2" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1111.1265v2" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="math-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="math-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="math.MP" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.flu-dyn" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1502.03944v1</id>
    <updated>2015-02-13T11:12:55Z</updated>
    <published>2015-02-13T11:12:55Z</published>
    <title>Pressure Responses of a Vertically Hydraulic Fractured Well in a
  Reservoir with Fractal Structure</title>
    <summary>  We obtain an analytical solution for the pressure-transient behavior of a
vertically hydraulic fractured well in a heterogeneous reservoir. The
heterogeneity of the reservoir is modeled by using the concept of fractal
geometry. Such reservoirs are called fractal reservoirs. According to the
theory of fractional calculus, a temporal fractional derivative is applied to
incorporate the memory properties of the fractal reservoir. The effect of
different parameters on the computed wellbore pressure is fully investigated by
various synthetic examples.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Kambiz Razminia</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Abolhassan Razminia</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Delfim F. M. Torres</name>
    </author>
    <arxiv:doi xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">10.1016/j.amc.2014.12.124</arxiv:doi>
    <link title="doi" href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.amc.2014.12.124" rel="related"/>
    <arxiv:comment xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">This is a preprint of a paper whose final and definite form is
  published in Applied Mathematics and Computation, ISSN: 0096-3003. Submitted
  01/July/2014; revised 20/Dec/2014; accepted 29/Dec/2014. Published version
  available at http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.amc.2014.12.124</arxiv:comment>
    <arxiv:journal_ref xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">Appl. Math. Comput. 257 (2015), 374--380</arxiv:journal_ref>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1502.03944v1" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1502.03944v1" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="physics.flu-dyn" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.flu-dyn" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1609.01237v1</id>
    <updated>2016-09-05T17:58:47Z</updated>
    <published>2016-09-05T17:58:47Z</published>
    <title>Blade-shaped (PKN) Hydraulic Fracture Driven By A Turbulent Fluid In An
  Impermeable Rock</title>
    <summary>  High flow rate, water-driven hydraulic fractures are more common now than
ever in the oil and gas industry. Although the fractures are small, the high
injection rate and low viscosity of the water, lead to high Reynolds numbers
and potentially turbulence in the fracture. Here we present a semi-analytical
solution for a blade-shaped (PKN) geometry hydraulic fracture driven by a
turbulent fluid in the limit of zero fluid leak-off to the formation. We model
the turbulence in the PKN fracture using the Gaukler-Manning-Strickler
parametrization, which relates the the flow rate of the water to the pressure
gradient along the fracture. The key parameter in this relation is the
Darcy-Weisbach friction factor for the roughness of the crack wall. Coupling
this turbulence parametrization with conservation of mass allows us to write a
nonlinear pde for the crack width as a function of space and time. By way of a
similarity ansatz, we obtain a semi-analytical solution using an orthogonal
polynomial series. Embedding the asymptotic behavior near the fracture tip into
the polynomial series, we find very rapid convergence: a suitably accurate
solution is obtained with two terms of the series. This closed-form solution
facilitates clear comparisons between the results and parameters for laminar
and turbulent hydraulic fractures. In particular, it resolves one of the well
known problems whereby calibration of models to data has difficulty
simultaneously matching the hydraulic fracture length and wellbore pressure.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Navid Zolfaghari</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Colin R. Meyer</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Andrew P. Bunger</name>
    </author>
    <arxiv:comment xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">Main Article: 25 pages, 9 figures, To appear in Journal of
  Engineering Mechanics, ASCE, 2016. Supplementary Data: 13 pages, 4 figures</arxiv:comment>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1609.01237v1" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1609.01237v1" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.flu-dyn" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
