<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <link href="http://arxiv.org/api/query?search_query%3Dall%3Ageomechanics%26id_list%3D%26start%3D0%26max_results%3D20" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <title type="html">ArXiv Query: search_query=all:geomechanics&amp;id_list=&amp;start=0&amp;max_results=20</title>
  <id>http://arxiv.org/api/bLfaOj55q+FYvI5nA/8vLwY4zWc</id>
  <updated>2018-03-02T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
  <opensearch:totalResults xmlns:opensearch="http://a9.com/-/spec/opensearch/1.1/">36</opensearch:totalResults>
  <opensearch:startIndex xmlns:opensearch="http://a9.com/-/spec/opensearch/1.1/">0</opensearch:startIndex>
  <opensearch:itemsPerPage xmlns:opensearch="http://a9.com/-/spec/opensearch/1.1/">20</opensearch:itemsPerPage>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1609.00579v1</id>
    <updated>2016-09-02T12:46:20Z</updated>
    <published>2016-09-02T12:46:20Z</published>
    <title>Modelling Geomechanical Impact of CO2 Injection Using Precomputed
  Response Functions</title>
    <summary>  When injecting CO2 or other fluids into a geological formation, pressure
plays an important role both as a driver of flow and as a risk factor for
mechanical integrity.
  The full effect of geomechanics on aquifer flow can only be captured using a
coupled flow-geomechanics model. In order to solve this computationally
expensive system, various strategies have been put forwards over the years,
with some of the best current methods based on sequential splitting.
  In the present work, we seek to approximate the full geomechanical effect on
flow without the need of coupling with a geomechanics solver during simulation,
and at a computational cost comparable to that of an uncoupled model. We do
this by means of precomputed pressure response functions. At grid model
generation time, a geomechanics solver is used to compute the mechanical
response of the aquifer for a set of pressure fields. The relevant information
from these responses is then stored in a compact form and embedded with the
grid model.
  We test the accuracy and computational performance of our approach on a
simple 2D and a more complex 3D model, and compare the results with those
produced by a fully coupled approach as well as from a simple decoupled method
based on Geertsma's uniaxial expansion coefficient.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Odd Andersen</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Halvor M. Nilsen</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Sarah E. Gasda</name>
    </author>
    <arxiv:comment xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">Preprint, ECMOR XV</arxiv:comment>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1609.00579v1" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1609.00579v1" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="J.2" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1710.11464v1</id>
    <updated>2017-10-26T16:47:20Z</updated>
    <published>2017-10-26T16:47:20Z</published>
    <title>What Factors Control Shale Gas Production and Production Decline Trend
  in Fractured Systems: A Comprehensive Analysis and Investigation</title>
    <summary>  A multi-physics model for shale gas production in fractured system, that
couples real gas property, nano-flow mechanism and geomechanics
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>HanYi Wang</name>
    </author>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1710.11464v1" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1710.11464v1" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1512.04581v2</id>
    <updated>2017-08-18T07:15:39Z</updated>
    <published>2015-12-15T07:07:25Z</published>
    <title>Testing a coupled hydro-thermo-chemo-geomechanical model for gas hydrate
  bearing sediments using triaxial compression lab experiments</title>
    <summary>  Natural gas hydrates are considered a potential resource for gas production
on industrial scales. Gas hydrates contribute to the strength and stiffness of
the hydrate-bearing sediments. During gas production, the geomechanical
stability of the sediment is compromised. Due to the potential geotechnical
risks and process management issues, the mechanical behavior of the gas
hydrate-bearing sediments needs to be carefully considered. In this study, we
describe a coupling concept that simplifies the mathematical description of the
complex interactions occuring during gas production by isolating the effects of
sediment deformation and hydrate phase changes. Central to this coupling
concept is the assumption that the soil grains form the load-bearing solid
skeleton, while the gas hydrate enhances the mechanical properties of this
skeleton. We focus on testing this coupling concept in capturing the overall
impact of geomechanics on gas production behavior though numerical simulation
of a high-pressure isotropic compression experiment combined with methane
hydrate formation and dissociation. We consider a linear-elastic stress-strain
relationship because it is uniquely defined and easy to calibrate. Since, in
reality, the geomechanical response of the hydrate bearing sediment is
typically inelastic and is characterized by a significant shear-volumetric
coupling, we control the experiment very carefully in order to keep the sample
deformations small and well within the assumptions of poro-elasticity. The
closely co-ordinated experimental and numerical procedures enable us to
validate the proposed simplified geomechanics-to-flow coupling, and set an
important precursor towards enhancing our coupled hydro-geomechanical hydrate
reservoir simulator with more suitable elasto-plastic constitutive models.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Shubhangi Gupta</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Christian Deusner</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Matthias Haeckel</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Rainer Helmig</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Barbara Wohlmuth</name>
    </author>
    <arxiv:doi xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">10.1002/2017GC006901</arxiv:doi>
    <link title="doi" href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/2017GC006901" rel="related"/>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1512.04581v2" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1512.04581v2" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="math.NA" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="math.NA" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="math.DS" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1704.01064v1</id>
    <updated>2017-03-27T13:26:05Z</updated>
    <published>2017-03-27T13:26:05Z</published>
    <title>Direct observation of coupled geochemical and geomechanical impacts on
  chalk microstructural evolution under elevated CO2 pressure. Part I</title>
    <summary>  The dissolution of porous media in a geologic formation induced by the
injection of massive amounts of CO2 can undermine the mechanical stability of
the formation structure before carbon mineralization takes place. The
geomechanical impact of geologic carbon storage is therefore closely related to
the structural sustainability of the chosen reservoir as well as the
probability of buoyancy driven CO2 leakage through caprocks. Here we show, with
a combination of ex situ nanotomography and in situ microtomography, that the
presence of dissolved CO2 in water produces a homogeneous dissolution pattern
in natural chalk microstructure. This pattern stems from a greater apparent
solubility of chalk and therefore a greater reactive subvolume in a sample.
When a porous medium dissolves homogeneously in an imposed flow field, three
geomechanical effects were observed: material compaction, fracturing and grain
relocation. These phenomena demonstrated distinct feedbacks to the migration of
the dissolution front and severely complicated the infiltration instability
problem. We conclude that the presence of dissolved CO2 makes the dissolution
front less susceptible to spatial and temporal perturbations in the strongly
coupled geochemical and geomechanical processes.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Y. Yang</name>
      <arxiv:affiliation xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">Nano-Science Center, Department of Chemistry, University of Copenhagen</arxiv:affiliation>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>S. S. Hakim</name>
      <arxiv:affiliation xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">Nano-Science Center, Department of Chemistry, University of Copenhagen</arxiv:affiliation>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>S. Bruns</name>
      <arxiv:affiliation xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">Nano-Science Center, Department of Chemistry, University of Copenhagen</arxiv:affiliation>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>M. Rogowska</name>
      <arxiv:affiliation xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">Nano-Science Center, Department of Chemistry, University of Copenhagen</arxiv:affiliation>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>S. Boehnert</name>
      <arxiv:affiliation xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">Nano-Science Center, Department of Chemistry, University of Copenhagen</arxiv:affiliation>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>J. U. Hammel</name>
      <arxiv:affiliation xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">Helmholtz-Zentrum Geesthacht, Germany</arxiv:affiliation>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>S. L. S. Stipp</name>
      <arxiv:affiliation xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">Nano-Science Center, Department of Chemistry, University of Copenhagen</arxiv:affiliation>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>H. O. Sørensen</name>
      <arxiv:affiliation xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">Nano-Science Center, Department of Chemistry, University of Copenhagen</arxiv:affiliation>
    </author>
    <arxiv:comment xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">43 pages, 16 figures</arxiv:comment>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1704.01064v1" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1704.01064v1" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="nlin.AO" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1304.4895v1</id>
    <updated>2013-04-17T17:26:51Z</updated>
    <published>2013-04-17T17:26:51Z</published>
    <title>Pore-scale modeling of fluid-particles interaction and emerging
  poromechanical effects</title>
    <summary>  A micro-hydromechanical model for granular materials is presented. It
combines the discrete element method (DEM) for the modeling of the solid phase
and a pore-scale finite volume (PFV) formulation for the flow of an
incompressible pore fluid. The coupling equations are derived and contrasted
against the equations of conventional poroelasticity. An analogy is found
between the DEM-PFV coupling and Biot's theory in the limit case of
incompressible phases. The simulation of an oedometer test validates the
coupling scheme and demonstrates the ability of the model to capture strong
poromechanical effects. A detailed analysis of microscale strain and stress
confirms the analogy with poroelasticity. An immersed deposition problem is
finally simulated and shows the potential of the method to handle phase
transitions.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Emanuele Catalano</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Bruno Chareyre</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Eric Barthélémy</name>
    </author>
    <arxiv:doi xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">10.1002/nag.2198</arxiv:doi>
    <link title="doi" href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/nag.2198" rel="related"/>
    <arxiv:comment xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">accepted in Int. Journal for Numerical and Analytical Methods in
  Geomechanics</arxiv:comment>
    <arxiv:journal_ref xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">Int. J. for Numerical and Analytical Methods in Geomechanics.
  38(1), 2014, p. 51-71</arxiv:journal_ref>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1304.4895v1" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1304.4895v1" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="cond-mat.soft" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="cond-mat.soft" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="cond-mat.mtrl-sci" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1511.00466v2</id>
    <updated>2016-03-01T11:11:53Z</updated>
    <published>2015-11-02T12:19:19Z</published>
    <title>Multi-rate time stepping schemes for hydro-geomechanical model for
  subsurface methane hydrate reservoirs</title>
    <summary>  We present an extrapolation-based semi-implicit multirate time stepping (MRT)
scheme and a compound-fast MRT scheme for a naturally partitioned,
multi-time-scale hydro-geomechanical hydrate reservoir model. We evaluate the
performance of the two MRT methods compared to an iteratively coupled solution
scheme and discuss their advantages and disadvantages. The performance of the
two MRT methods is evaluated in terms of speed-up and accuracy by comparison to
an iteratively coupled solution scheme. We observe that the extrapolation-based
semi-implicit method gives a higher speed-up but is strongly dependent on the
relative time scales of the latent (slow) and active (fast) components. On the
other hand, the compound-fast method is more robust and less sensitive to the
relative time scales, but gives lower speed up as compared to the semi-implicit
method, especially when the relative time scales of the active and latent
components are comparable.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Shubhangi Gupta</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Barbara I. Wohlmuth</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Rainer Helmig</name>
    </author>
    <arxiv:doi xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">10.1016/j.advwatres.2016.02.013</arxiv:doi>
    <link title="doi" href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.advwatres.2016.02.013" rel="related"/>
    <arxiv:comment xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">Advances in Water Resources</arxiv:comment>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1511.00466v2" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1511.00466v2" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="math.NA" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="math.NA" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1606.09508v2</id>
    <updated>2017-02-08T09:06:28Z</updated>
    <published>2016-06-30T14:30:02Z</published>
    <title>Virtual Element Method for geomechanics on reservoir grids</title>
    <summary>  In this paper we study the use of Virtual Element method for geomechanics.
Our emphasis is on applications to reservoir simulations. The physical
processes that form the reservoirs, such as sedimentation, erosion and
faulting, lead to complex geometrical structures. A minimal representation,
with respect to the physical parameters of the system, then naturally leads to
general polyhedral grids. Numerical methods which can directly handle this
representation will be highly favorable, in particular in the setting of
advanced work-flows. The Virtual Element method is a promising candidate to
solve the linear elasticity equations on such models. In this paper, we
investigate some of the limits of the VEM method when used on reservoir models.
First, we demonstrate that care must be taken to make the method robust for
highly elongated cells, which is common in these applications, and show the
importance of calculating forces in terms of traction on the boundary of the
elements for elongated distorted cells. Second, we study the effect of
triangulations on the surfaces of curved faces, which also naturally occur in
subsurface models. We also demonstrate how a more stable regularization term
for reservoir application can be derived.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Odd Andersen</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Halvor M. Nilsen</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Xavier Raynaud</name>
    </author>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1606.09508v2" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1606.09508v2" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="math.NA" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="math.NA" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1610.07120v1</id>
    <updated>2016-10-23T03:38:02Z</updated>
    <published>2016-10-23T03:38:02Z</published>
    <title>Iterative coupling of flow, geomechanics and adaptive phase-field
  fracture including level-set crack width approaches</title>
    <summary>  In this work, we present numerical studies of fixed-stress iterative coupling
for solving flow and geomechanics with propagating fractures in a porous
medium. Specifically, fracture propagations are described by employing a
phase-field approach. The extension to fixed-stress splitting to propagating
phase-field fractures and systematic investigation of its properties are
important enhancements to existing studies. Moreover, we provide an accurate
computation of the fracture opening using level-set approaches and a subsequent
finite element interpolation of the width. The latter enters as fracture
permeability into the pressure diffraction problem which is crucial for fluid
filled fractures. Our developments are substantiated with several numerical
tests that include comparisons of computational cost for iterative coupling and
nonlinear and linear iterations as well as convergence studies in space and
time.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Sanghyun Lee</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Thomas Wick</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Mary F. Wheeler</name>
    </author>
    <arxiv:doi xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">10.1016/j.cam.2016.10.022</arxiv:doi>
    <link title="doi" href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.cam.2016.10.022" rel="related"/>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1610.07120v1" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1610.07120v1" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="math.NA" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="math.NA" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1303.5304v1</id>
    <updated>2013-03-21T15:41:46Z</updated>
    <published>2013-03-21T15:41:46Z</published>
    <title>A laboratory investigation of thermally induced pore pressures in the
  Callovo-Oxfordian Claystone</title>
    <summary>  In the framework of research into radioactive waste disposal, it was decided
to investigate the thermally induce pore pressure occurring in the
Callovo-Oxfordian claystone, a possible host rock in which the ANDRA
underground laboratory of Bure (East of France) has been excavated. Thermal
pore pressures appear in low permeability soils and rocks because the thermal
expansion coefficient of water is significantly higher than that of the solid
grains (Campanella and Mitchell; 1968 [1], Ghabezloo and Sulem; 2009 [2]). This
phenomenon has clearly been observed in various in-situ heating tests conducted
in Opalinus claystone in the Mont-Terri Underground Research Laboratory (URL)
in Switzerland (HE-D test) and in Callovo-Oxfordian (COx) claystone in the Bure
URL in France (TER test, Wileveau and Su; 2007 [3]) The processes of coring,
transportation, storage and specimen trimming induce some desaturation in the
sample. Due to the very low permeability (10-20 m2) of the COx claystone, a
long period of time is necessary to properly resaturate the sample, a mandatory
condition to satisfactorily investigate thermal pressurisation. Particular
emphasis was hence put on the previous saturation procedure that was carried
out under in-situ effective stress condition. Thermal pressurization has been
investigated by performing undrained heating tests while measuring pore
pressures changes in a specially adapted thermal isotropic compression cell.
Special care was devoted to calibration procedures to account for the effects
of the system on the pore pressure measurements. The thermal pressurization
coefficient measured appeared to change with temperature, mainly because of the
changes with temperature of both the water thermal expansion coefficient of
water and the drained compression coefficient of the claystone.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Mehrdokht Mohajerani</name>
      <arxiv:affiliation xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">ANDRA</arxiv:affiliation>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Pierre Delage</name>
      <arxiv:affiliation xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">ANDRA</arxiv:affiliation>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Jean Sulem</name>
      <arxiv:affiliation xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">ANDRA</arxiv:affiliation>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Mohammad Monfared</name>
      <arxiv:affiliation xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">ANDRA</arxiv:affiliation>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Anh-Minh Tang</name>
      <arxiv:affiliation xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">ANDRA</arxiv:affiliation>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Behrouz Gatmiri</name>
      <arxiv:affiliation xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">ANDRA</arxiv:affiliation>
    </author>
    <arxiv:journal_ref xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">International Journal of Rock Mechanics and Mining Science \&amp;
  Geomechanics Abstracts / International Journal of Rock Mechanics and Mining
  Sciences \&amp; Geomechanics Abstracts; International Journal of Rock Mechanics
  and Mining Sciences and Geomechanics Abstra 52 (2012) 112-121</arxiv:journal_ref>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1303.5304v1" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1303.5304v1" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/0902.1309v1</id>
    <updated>2009-02-08T13:31:29Z</updated>
    <published>2009-02-08T13:31:29Z</published>
    <title>Numerical Simulation of Gas Storage Caverns in Qom Region</title>
    <summary>  The rock mechanical design of gas storage cavern in salt requires the
analysis of the stability and the usability of the cavern over the planned
operating time period. The design includes the build up of a rock mass model
and a numerical model taking into account the geological situation, load
condition, geometrical condition, and material parameters. In this paper
multiple caverns in salt formation with geological and geomechanical situation
in Qom (central part of Iran) was investigated a using creep model. Minimum
safe center to center distances (CTCD) of multiple horizontal caverns also were
studied. CTCD of caverns interact at less than two times of cavern diameter.
With increasing the CTCD to 2.5 times cavern diameters, diminish most
interaction.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Mostafa Sharifzadeh</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Ali Moradi Ghasr</name>
    </author>
    <arxiv:comment xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">ARMS Conferences (2006)</arxiv:comment>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/0902.1309v1" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/0902.1309v1" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1206.6711v1</id>
    <updated>2012-05-29T12:27:37Z</updated>
    <published>2012-05-29T12:27:37Z</published>
    <title>L'approche energetique en mecanique des materiaux granulaires</title>
    <summary>  This communication establishes first, that basis of discontinuous granular
materials mechanics, are the explicit result of a new approach of the physics
of energy dissipation by friction, and second, that these mechanics of
discontinua, transposed to the equivalent continuous media, as used in
geomechanics, is directly responsible for a large set of practical properties
of these materials, part of the fundamentals of Soil Mechanics. These physics
of energy dissipation are developped on the original concept of energy rate
tensor of internal actions.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>E. Frossard</name>
    </author>
    <arxiv:comment xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">57 pages</arxiv:comment>
    <arxiv:journal_ref xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">Poudres &amp; Grains NS2, 1-56, (2001), ISSN 1257-3957</arxiv:journal_ref>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1206.6711v1" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1206.6711v1" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="physics.flu-dyn" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.flu-dyn" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1408.0645v2</id>
    <updated>2014-09-29T05:15:48Z</updated>
    <published>2014-08-04T11:20:38Z</published>
    <title>Robust joint full-waveform inversion of time-lapse seismic data sets
  with total-variation regularization</title>
    <summary>  We present a technique for reconstructing subsurface velocity model changes
from time-lapse seismic survey data using full-waveform inversion (FWI). The
technique is based on simultaneously inverting multiple survey vintages, with
model difference regularization using the total variation (TV) seminorm. We
compare the new TV-regularized time-lapse FWI with the $L_2$-regularized joint
inversion proposed in our earlier work, using synthetic data sets that exhibit
survey repeatability issues. The results demonstrate clear advantages of the
proposed TV-regularized joint inversion over alternatives methods for
recovering production-induced model changes that are due to both fluid
substitution and geomechanical effects.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Musa Maharramov</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Biondo Biondi</name>
    </author>
    <arxiv:comment xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">10 pages, 6 figures</arxiv:comment>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1408.0645v2" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1408.0645v2" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="65Z05" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1505.05694v1</id>
    <updated>2015-05-21T12:19:20Z</updated>
    <published>2015-05-21T12:19:20Z</published>
    <title>Total-variation minimization with bound constraints</title>
    <summary>  We present a powerful and easy-to-implement algorithm for solving constrained
optimization problems that involve $L_1$/total-variation regularization terms,
and both equality and inequality constraints. We discuss the relationship of
our method to earlier works of Goldstein and Osher (2009) and Chartrand and
Wohlberg (2010), and demonstrate that our approach is a combination of the
augmented Lagrangian method with splitting and model projection. We test the
method on a geomechanical problem and invert highly compartmentalized pressure
change from noisy surface uplift observations. We conclude the paper with a
discussion of possible extension to a wide class of regularized optimization
problems with bound and equality constraints.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Musa Maharramov</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Stewart A. Levin</name>
    </author>
    <arxiv:comment xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">8 pages, 6 figures</arxiv:comment>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1505.05694v1" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1505.05694v1" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="math.OC" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="math.OC" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="80M50" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="G.1.6; J.2" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1711.02579v1</id>
    <updated>2017-11-02T17:58:16Z</updated>
    <published>2017-11-02T17:58:16Z</published>
    <title>A Numerical Study of Thermal-Hydraulic-Mechanical (THM) Simulation with
  the Application of Thermal Recovery in Fractured Shale Gas Reservoirs</title>
    <summary>  We presented a general multi-physics model for shale gas flow in fractured
systems, first the first time, with fully coupled thermal-hydraulic-mechanical
(THM) properties. The impact of gas adsorption, real gas properties, gas flow
in nano-scale pore space and geomechanics effects on total gas flow capacity
are investigated. We also showed that by elevating shale rock temperature, the
characteristic of gas adsorption behavior can be substantially altered.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>HanYi Wang</name>
    </author>
    <arxiv:comment xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">arXiv admin note: text overlap with arXiv:1710.11464</arxiv:comment>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1711.02579v1" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1711.02579v1" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1802.00949v1</id>
    <updated>2018-02-03T10:17:06Z</updated>
    <published>2018-02-03T10:17:06Z</published>
    <title>A parallel-in-time fixed-stress splitting method for Biot's
  consolidation model</title>
    <summary>  In this work, we study the parallel-in-time iterative solution of coupled
flow and geomechanics in porous media, modelled by a two-field formulation of
the Biot's equations. In particular, we propose a new version of the fixed
stress splitting method, which has been widely used as solution method of these
problems. This new approach forgets about the sequential nature of the temporal
variable and considers the time direction as a further direction for
parallelization. We present a rigorous convergence analysis of the method and a
numerical experiment to demonstrate the robust behaviour of the algorithm.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Manuel Borregales</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Kundan Kumar</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Florin Adrian Radu</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Carmen Rodrigo</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Francisco José Gaspar</name>
    </author>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1802.00949v1" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1802.00949v1" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="math.NA" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="math.NA" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1802.04256v1</id>
    <updated>2018-02-11T15:59:52Z</updated>
    <published>2018-02-11T15:59:52Z</published>
    <title>GeoMFree3D: An Under-Development Meshfree Software Package for
  Geomechanics</title>
    <summary>  This paper briefly reports the GeoMFree3D, a meshfree / meshless software
package designed for analyzing the problems of large deformations and crack
propagations of rock and soil masses in geotechnics. The GeoMFree3D is
developed based on the meshfree RPIM, and accelerated by exploiting the
parallel computing on multi-core CPU and many-core GPU. The GeoMFree3D is
currently being under intensive developments. To demonstrate the correctness
and effectiveness of the GeoMFree3D, several simple verification examples are
presented in this paper. Moreover, future work on the development of the
GeoMFree3D is introduced.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Gang Mei</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Nengxiong Xu</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Liangliang Xu</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Yazhe Li</name>
    </author>
    <arxiv:comment xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">5 figures</arxiv:comment>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1802.04256v1" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1802.04256v1" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="physics.comp-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.comp-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="cs.CE" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="math.NA" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1508.01421v1</id>
    <updated>2015-08-06T14:39:00Z</updated>
    <published>2015-08-06T14:39:00Z</published>
    <title>Non-Isothermal, Multi-phase, Multi-component Flows through Deformable
  Methane Hydrate Reservoirs</title>
    <summary>  We present a hydro-geomechanical model for subsurface methane hydrate
systems. Our model considers kinetic hydrate phase change and non-isothermal,
multi-phase, multi-component flow in elastically deforming soils. The model
accounts for the effects of hydrate phase change and pore pressure changes on
the mechanical properties of the soil, and also for the effect of soil
deformation on the fluid-solid interaction properties relevant to reaction and
transport processes (e.g., permeability, capillary pressure, reaction surface
area). We discuss a 'cause-effect' based decoupling strategy for the model and
present our numerical discretization and solution scheme. We then identify the
important model components and couplings which are most vital for a
hydro-geomechanical hydrate simulator, namely, 1) dissociation kinetics, 2)
hydrate phase change coupled with non-isothermal two phase two component flow,
3) two phase flow coupled with linear elasticity (poroelasticity coupling), and
finally 4) hydrate phase change coupled with poroelasticity
(kinetics-poroelasticity coupling) and present numerical examples where, for
each example, one of the aforementioned model components/couplings is isolated.
A special emphasis is laid on the kinetics-poroelasticity coupling. We also
present a more complex 3D example based on a subsurface hydrate reservoir which
is destabilized through depressurization using a low pressure gas well. In this
example, we simulate the melting of hydrate, methane gas generation, and the
resulting ground subsidence and stress build-up in the vicinity of the well.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Shubhangi Gupta</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Rainer Helmig</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Barbara Wohlmuth</name>
    </author>
    <arxiv:doi xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">10.1007/s10596-015-9520-9</arxiv:doi>
    <link title="doi" href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s10596-015-9520-9" rel="related"/>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1508.01421v1" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1508.01421v1" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="math.NA" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="math.NA" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="74F10, 74F25, 76S05, 76V05" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/math/0510066v3</id>
    <updated>2006-03-14T15:08:43Z</updated>
    <published>2005-10-04T08:55:20Z</published>
    <title>Modeling 1-D elastic P-waves in a fractured rock with hyperbolic jump
  conditions</title>
    <summary>  The propagation of elastic waves in a fractured rock is investigated, both
theoretically and numerically. Outside the fractures, the propagation of
compressional waves is described in the simple framework of one-dimensional
linear elastodynamics. The focus here is on the interactions between the waves
and fractures: for this purpose, the mechanical behavior of the fractures is
modeled using nonlinear jump conditions deduced from the Bandis-Barton model
classicaly used in geomechanics. Well-posedness of the initial-boundary value
problem thus obtained is proved. Numerical modeling is performed by coupling a
time-domain finite-difference scheme with an interface method accounting for
the jump conditions. The numerical experiments show the effects of contact
nonlinearities. The harmonics generated may provide a non-destructive means of
evaluating the mechanical properties of fractures.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Bruno Lombard</name>
      <arxiv:affiliation xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">LMA</arxiv:affiliation>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Joël Piraux</name>
      <arxiv:affiliation xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">LMA</arxiv:affiliation>
    </author>
    <arxiv:comment xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">accepted and to be published in the Journal of Computational and
  Applied Mathematics</arxiv:comment>
    <arxiv:journal_ref xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">Journal of Computational and applied mathematics 204, 2 (2007)
  292-305</arxiv:journal_ref>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/math/0510066v3" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/math/0510066v3" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="math.NA" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="math.NA" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.class-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="02.60.Cb, 02.70.Bf, 43.25.+y, 46.50.+a" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/0808.2009v1</id>
    <updated>2008-08-14T15:29:35Z</updated>
    <published>2008-08-14T15:29:35Z</published>
    <title>Thermo-Poro-Mechanical Properties of Clayey Gouge and Application to
  Rapid Fault Shearing</title>
    <summary>  In this paper, the mechanism of fault pressurization in rapid slip events is
analyzed on the basis of a complete characterization of the
thermo-poro-mechanical behavior of a clayey gouge extracted at 760m depth in
Aigion fault in the active seismic zone of the Gulf of Corinth, Greece. It is
shown that the thermally collapsible character of this clayey gouge can be
responsible for a dramatic reduction of effective stress and a full
fluidization of the material. The thickness of the 'ultra localized' zone of
highly strained material is a key parameter that controls the competing
phenomena of pore pressure increase leading to fluidization of the fault gouge
and temperature increase leading to pore fluid vaporization.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Jean Sulem</name>
      <arxiv:affiliation xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">ENPC-Cermes</arxiv:affiliation>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Paul Lazar</name>
      <arxiv:affiliation xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">ENPC-Cermes</arxiv:affiliation>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Ioannis Vardoulakis</name>
    </author>
    <arxiv:doi xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">10.1002/nag.584</arxiv:doi>
    <link title="doi" href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/nag.584" rel="related"/>
    <arxiv:journal_ref xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">International Journal for Numerical and Analytical Methods in
  Geomechanics 31, 3 (2007) 523-540</arxiv:journal_ref>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/0808.2009v1" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/0808.2009v1" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="physics.class-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.class-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>http://arxiv.org/abs/1005.3439v4</id>
    <updated>2011-08-23T23:22:55Z</updated>
    <published>2010-05-19T13:38:15Z</published>
    <title>Small World Property of a Rock Joint(Complexity of Frictional
  Interfaces: A Complex Network Perspective)</title>
    <summary>  The shear strength and stick-slip behavior of a rough rock joint are analyzed
using the complex network approach. We develop a network approach on
correlation patterns of void spaces of an evolvable rough fracture (crack type
II). Correlation among networks properties with the hydro -mechanical
attributes (obtained from experimental tests) of fracture before and after slip
is the direct result of the revealed non-contacts networks. Joint distribution
of locally and globally filtered correlation gives a close relation to the
contact zones attachment-detachment sequences through the evolution of shear
strength of the rock joint. Especially spread of node's degree rate to spread
of clustering coefficient rate yielded possible stick and slip sequences during
the displacements. Our method can be developed to investigate the complexity of
stick-slip behavior of faults as well as energy /stress localization on
crumpled shells/sheets in which ridge networks are controlling the energy
distribution.
</summary>
    <author>
      <name>Hamed O. Ghaffari</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>M. Sharifzadeh</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>E. Evgin</name>
    </author>
    <arxiv:doi xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">10.1080/17486025.2012.727036</arxiv:doi>
    <link title="doi" href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/17486025.2012.727036" rel="related"/>
    <arxiv:journal_ref xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom">Geomechanics and Geoengineering: An International Journal,2012</arxiv:journal_ref>
    <link href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1005.3439v4" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
    <link title="pdf" href="http://arxiv.org/pdf/1005.3439v4" rel="related" type="application/pdf"/>
    <arxiv:primary_category xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="physics.geo-ph" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="cond-mat.dis-nn" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="cs.CE" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
    <category term="nlin.AO" scheme="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
